<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Characters of a sincere heart and the comforts thereof collected out of the Word of God by Hen. Wilkinson.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1616-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66073</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27587</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09959986</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09959986</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44418</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66073)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44418)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1370:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Characters of a sincere heart and the comforts thereof collected out of the Word of God by Hen. Wilkinson.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1616-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 121, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield for Ric. Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:1"/>
            <p>CHARACTERS OF A SINCERE HEART, And the COMFORTS thereof. Collected out of the. WORD OF GOD,</p>
            <p>By HEN-WILKINSON, D. D. Late Principal of <hi>Magdalen Hall</hi> in the Univerſity of <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 Sam. 16. 7. <hi>Man looketh on the outward appearance, but Lord looketh on the heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pſal. 51. 6. <hi>Behold thou deſireſt truth in the inward parts<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and in the hidden part thou ſhalt make me to know wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>L. LICHFIELD,</hi> Printer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e Univerſity, for <hi>RIC. DAVIS,</hi> Anno Domini, 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the much Honoured and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady HESTER HONYWOOD of</hi> Marks-Hall <hi>in the County of of</hi> Eſſex: Grace, Mercy, and Peace from God our Father, and Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Madame,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>EDICATIONS of Books to Perſons of great rank and Quality, are of great antiquity, for</hi> St. Luke <hi>Dedicates</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 1. 3. Act. 1. 1.</note> 
               <hi>two Treatiſes</hi> To the moſt excellent Theophilus. <hi>And now a daies it's uſual to dedicate Books to ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, who are (probably) ready to approve them by their Patronage and practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:3"/>
            <p>As to my own concernment, I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prefix your name to this little Treatiſe, not only to acknowledge with all thankfulneſs, the many great Favours, which I have received from you, but eſpeciall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to preſent thoſe things to your view whereof you have had ſo large experience as you can give Testimony to the truth of them, both as to your judgement and affections.</p>
            <p>I therefore am your remembrancer of thoſe things, whereof (as I doubt not) you have experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and my deſign is to comfort you with thoſe comforts, wherewith I my ſelf have been comforted: It's the charge which the Angel gives unto the Church of <hi>Thyatira—But that which you have already, hold</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 25.</note> 
               <hi>faſt:</hi> And the Apoſtle's charge is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto that,—<hi>Let us hold faſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 23.</note> 
               <hi>the profeſſion of our faith without wavering, (for he is faithful that</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:3"/> 
               <hi>promiſed.)</hi> Likewiſe for ſelf exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and tryal of our eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for heaven, we are frequently commanded,—More particularly <hi>St. Paul</hi> chargeth the Corinthians, and us as well as them.—<hi>Examine your</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note> 
               <hi>ſelves: know ye not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you? except ye be Reprobates.</hi> So likewiſe the Church (after ſhe had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone great afflictions and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) makes this ſerious deliberate reſolution—<hi>Let us ſearch and try</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 40.</note> 
               <hi>our waies, and turn again to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You being (Madam) an old Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple, and an experienced Chriſtian, cannot but know, that it's a duty of great concernment, and in an eſpecial manner incumbent upon all faithful Miniſters to endeavour in their Preaching to diſtinguiſh the pretious from the vile: for ſo ſaith the Lord to the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah. If thou</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ier. 15. 19.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:4"/> take forth the pretiou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the vile, thou ſhalt be as my mouth: let them return unto thee but return thou not to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our bleſſed Lord and Saviour, the beſt Example and the exacteſt Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern for our imitation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Sermon which he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Mount, makes mention of</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Beatitudes, <hi>each of them being a rare diſcriminati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g character, whereby good and bad, bleſſed and curſed, are diſtinguiſhed one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: For if the poor in ſpirit be bleſſed, then the rich &amp; proud in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit are curſed; &amp; if the pure in heart be bleſſed, then the impu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in heart muſt be curſed, &amp;c. Becauſe of Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties there are contrary conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And Christ himſelf is the beſt Interpreter of himſelf, for when he pronounced bleſſings upon ſuch as</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 6. 20. 21. 22.</note> 
               <hi>were</hi> poor, and hungred, and wept, <note place="margin">v. 24, 25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>he pronounced</hi> woes <hi>againſt ſuch as</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:4"/> 
               <hi>were</hi> rich and full, and of whom all men ſpeak well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe our Saviour ſhewes the abſolute and indiſpenſible neceſſity of</hi> Regeneration and being born from above, <hi>as may appear by Chriſts an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to</hi> Nichodemus.—Jeſus anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſaid unto him, Verily, verily <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 3.</note> I ſay unto thee, except a man be born again he cannot ſee the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. <hi>And Regeneration is a Characteriſtick note of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between the old and new birth. Farther, Christ puts a vaſt differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between a good and a bad tree: For (ſaith he)</hi> A good tree cannot <note place="margin">Matt. 7. 18, 19, 20.</note> bring forth evil fruit, neither can a corrupt tree bring forth good fruit. Every tree that bringeth not good fruit is hewen down, and caſt into the fier, wherefore by their fruits you ſhall know them: <hi>And Chriſt makes</hi> Love one to another, <hi>a mark</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 35.</note> 
               <hi>af his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And after Chriſts Example, his Apoſtles lay down marks and ſignes to diſtinguiſh the good from the bad. For inſtance, How frequently, doth</hi> St. John <hi>preſs the grace of love, and lays it down as an infallible ſign of one that is tranſlated from death to life</hi>—We know that we have paſſed <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 14.</note> from death to life, becauſe we love the Brethren: He that loveth not his Brother abideth in death. <hi>Saint</hi> Peter <hi>expreſly manifests what we ſhould avoid</hi>—Wherefore laying <note place="margin">1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. 2. 1, 2, 3.</note> aſide all malice and guile, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocuſies, and envies, and all evil ſpeakings, <hi>&amp;c and he injoynes what we ſhould reduce unto practice,</hi> As new born babes, deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby. <hi>And it follows by way of Character, repreſenting ſuch who are new born babes in theſe words.</hi> If ſo be that ye have taſted that the Lord <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17.</note> is gracious. <hi>Saint</hi> Paul <hi>gives an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident
<pb facs="tcp:44418:5"/> ſign of ſuch who are in Chriſt by the new Creature wrought in them.</hi> Thefore if any man be in Chriſt he is a new Creature: old things are paſt away, behold all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come new. <hi>And, to mention only one more ſcripture to this purpoſe, The Apostle diſcovers a great difference between the old man and the new, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 21. 22, 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>thus Preſſeth our duty upon us:</hi> If ſo be that ye have been taught by him as the truth is in Jeſus, That ye put of concerning the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, the old man which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt according to the deceitful luſts: And be renewed in the ſpirit of your minde: and that ye put on the new man, which after God is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in righteouſneſs, and true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now having ſuch abundant war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from the example of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, I question not in the</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:6"/> 
               <hi>leaſt, but that in the exerciſe of our Miniſtry we obliged according to the Rule of the word of Gods to lay down Characters of a Regenerate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and to diſtinguiſh ſincere and real Profeſſors, from ſuch who are only Nominal and Hypocritical. Many there are who name the name of Chriſt, but depart not from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity: But it's the expreſs command of the word:</hi> And let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity. <hi>Many there are that content themſelves, with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Church of</hi> Sardis, <hi>to have only a bare name to live; But he is reproved by Chriſt,</hi> Rev. 3 1, 2. And unto the Angel of the Church in Sardis write, theſe things ſaith he <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 1. 2.</note> that hath the ſeaven ſpirits of God, and the ſeaven Stars, I know thy works, that thou haſt a name, that liveſt and art dead. Be watchful and
<pb facs="tcp:44418:6"/> ſtrengthen the things that are ready to dye: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I have not found thy works perfect before God. <hi>Many there are who reſt ſatisfied with a bare form, and deny the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs: But the Apoſtles command is</hi>—Having a form of godlineſs, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 5.</note> but denying the power thereof: from ſuch turn away.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Sincerity of the Heart is that which God requires.</hi> Behold thou deſireth truth in the inward parts: <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 6. Joſh. 34. 14. Ioh. 4. 24.</note> 
               <hi>God muſt be feared and ſerved in</hi> ſincerity and in truth: <hi>God is a ſpirit, and his worſhip muſt be a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual worſhip: So ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> God is a ſpirit and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit, and in truth. <hi>The fruits of the ſpirit are reck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d up by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle to be in</hi> all goodneſs, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and truth. <hi>Goodneſs may</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>be reckoned to the duties of the firſt</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:7"/> 
               <hi>Table, and righteouſneſs to the duties of the ſecond Table, but Truth</hi> (i e.) <hi>Sincerity, refers to both Tables reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectively. Sincerity is the ground of rejoycing, For (ſaith the Apoſtle)</hi> Our rejoycing is this, the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Cor. 1. 12.</note> of our Conſcience, that in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and godly ſincerity, not with fleſhly wiſdome, but by the grace of God, we have had our converſation, and more abundantly to you ward. <hi>And the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle prayes for the</hi> Philippians, That <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 10.</note> ye may approve things that are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, that ye may be ſincere, and without offence till the day of Chriſt. <hi>And although he is ſenſible of his own, and of his Brethrens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency for the great work of the Miniſtry, as may appear by that Queſtion which he propounds:</hi> And who is ſufficient for theſe things? <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Yet he makes this profeſſion of his</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:7"/> 
               <hi>own, and his brethrens ſincerity.</hi> For <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> we are not as many <note place="margin">v. 17.</note> which corrupt the word of God: but as of ſincerity, but as of God in the fight of God, ſpeak we in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To draw to a cloſe of this Epistle: It is the ſincerity of the Heart, which both to Miniſters and people is a great ground of conſolation. The grand deſign which I only drive at in this ſmall Treatiſe, is to ſtir up my ſelf and others, that every one in good earneſt may Chatechiſe his own heart, and propound this great need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Question.</hi> Is my heart ſincere with God? <hi>For anſwer to this queſtion, I have by way of Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, according to the Rule of the word of God, endeavoured to declare in ſeveral particulars, wherein the ſincerity of the heart conſists.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Treatiſe I preached as to</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:8"/> the ſubſtantials thereof, (which ſinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I have unlarged) in the publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ation at <hi>Cosfield</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you (much Honoured Madam) I of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Mite, or Teſtimony of my graceful acknowledgment of theſe many ſignal favours, which both my ſelf and my neareſt Relations have recieved from you, both in our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and health, God hath made you a worthy instrument to do good to many, and I hope you will fare the better for their prayers. That Bread which you have caſt upon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, you ſhall find after many daies. May the Lord lengthen out your daies, for the glory of God, and for your own good, and the good of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others: And may you be one of thoſe of whom the Pſalmiſt makes mention; <hi>Thoſe that be planted in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92. 13.</note> the houſe of the Lord ſhall flouriſh in the Courts of God; They ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:44418:8"/> ſtill bring forth fruit in old age; They ſhall be fat and flouriſhing. <hi>I commend your ſelf, and all your Relations, to the Gracious Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, beſeeching him to guide you by his counſell till he bring you to glory. I remain</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Sible Henningham in Eſſex, <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 1. 1674.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Madame</salute>
               <signed>Your Servant for Chriſt ſake, HEN. WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44418:9"/>
            <head>CHARACTERS OF A <hi>SINCERE HEART.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of Spiritual Poverty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt Character of a Sincere <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charact.</hi> 1. Spiritual Poverty.</note> Heart, is, <hi>Spiritual Poverty:</hi> And Spiritual Poverty conſiſts in emptying of the Heart to the utmoſt, of all and every thing, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is <hi>Self;</hi> as ſelf-love, ſelf-righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſelf-opinion, ſelf-ſufficiency, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonings and diſputings with fleſh and blood, and ſelf-confidence, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceit, and all manner of ſelf-ends, ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aims, and ſelf-deſigns, So that when a Chriſtian is wholly emptied of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and he hath learned that great and excellent Goſpel-Leſſon of <hi>Self-denyal,</hi> and he comprehends himſelf, as he is in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44418:10"/> himſelf only, nothing, and leſs then no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thing, and is vile in his own eyes, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> magnifies the riches of Gods mercy, and aſcribes all honour and glory to God ſuch a one is Sincere, &amp; upright hearted towards God. <hi>Jacob</hi> whom the Holy Ghoſt ſtiles <hi>a plain man, (i. e.)</hi> as <note n="*" place="margin">Taatum dicit ſuiſse ſimplicem; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> quidem pro integro &amp; ſincero at plurimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accipitur, <hi>Calv.</hi> Jacob viz. integer, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex: Graeci <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> alienus ab omni fraude dolo, &amp; callidatate, <hi>Mercer.</hi> in Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſome <note place="margin">Gen. 25. 27.</note> interpret, a ſincere and ſingle hearted man, was a man of an humble ſpirit, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his confeſſion, <hi>I am not worthy o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the leaſt of all thy mercies, and of all the truth which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy ſervant,</hi> Gen. 32. 10. <hi>David</hi> was poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſpirit, &amp; endowed with that excellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grace of Humilitie: For he was ſo vil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his own eyes, as he accounted himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a worm and no man,</hi> Pſal. 22. 6. and when the Lord ſent <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet to tell what great things God had, and would do, for him, as to take him <hi>from</hi> 2 Sam. 7. 8. and that he had <hi>cut off all his the Sheep Coat to be ruler over Iſrael, enemies,</hi> and <hi>made him a great name,</hi> ver. 9. and that he would fix the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, <hi>that they may dwell in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> place of their own, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ve no more,</hi> and that the Lord would <hi>make David an houſe;</hi> how <hi>David</hi> received theſe meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges from the Prophet, is apparent by the humility and thankfulneſs, whereof he gave a large teſtimony, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 18.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44418:10"/> 19. <hi>Then went King</hi> David <hi>in, and ſate before the Lord, and he ſaid, who am I, O Lord God? and what is my houſe, that thou haſt brought me hitherto? And this was yet a ſmall thing in thy ſight O Lord God; but thou haſt ſpoken alſo of thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants houſe, for a great while to come, and is this the manner of man, O Lord God? Agur</hi> was a wiſe man, and the more wiſe, becauſe the more humble, and the more eſteem'd of by God, by how much the more vile he was in his own opinion. His <note place="margin">Qui ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i vilis eſt Deo charus eſt. <hi>Born.</hi> Prov. 30. 2.</note> acknowledging himſelf <hi>to be more brutiſh then any man, and not to have the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of a man,</hi> plainly declares the lowlineſs and poverty of his ſpirit. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was the chiefeſt of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and more eminent in gifts, and graces, then any of them, yet he had ſo cheap and mean thoughts, and valuation of himſelf, as to confeſs that he was <hi>chief</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>of ſinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Every humble ſpirited perſon, who trades moſt at home, and negotiates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his own ſoul, in heart-ſearching, and ſelf-examination, thinks far worſe of himſelf, and is more abject in his own eies, then in the eies of the worſt of his enemies. Wherefore he is ſenſible of his forlorn and miſerable eſtate: He knows
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44418:11"/> himſelf to be poor, and indigent, and therefore he goes to Chriſt to inrich him. He apprehends himſelf blind, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or knowing nothing as he ought to know, and therefore he begs eye-ſalve and a ſpirit of illumination from Jeſus Chriſt. He is ſenſible of his nakedneſs, and therefore he goes to Chriſt for cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, knowing that the immaculate robes of Chriſts righteouſnes can alone cloath and cover his nakedneſs. For this is that ſoul-ſaving Counſel, which Chriſt gives to the Angel of the Church of the <hi>Laodiceans,—I counſel thee to buy of me Gold tryed in the fire, that thou may'ſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 18. <hi>Suadendi no impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randi verbo utitur Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, quo illorum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundat inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni em qui ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi violenter trahantur non arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trantur ſe a Domino ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitos, tractos vel vocalos.</hi> Bulling. 1 Pet. 1. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>be rich, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd white rayment, that thou may'ſt be cloathed, that the ſhame of thy nakedneſs do not appear, and anoint thine eies with eie-ſalve that thou may'ſt ſee.</hi> By Gold we are to underſtand true grace, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>true faith, which is much more preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous then Gold,</hi> and this faith is not an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary faith, but 'tis a tryed faith, for its ſaid <hi>tryed in the fire, (i. e.)</hi> ſuch a faith that is genuine, and of the right ſtamp, that can endure the tryal of the ſword, and the tryal of afflictions though they be fiery. Further, by <hi>white rayment</hi> we are to underſtand, the unſpotted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent robes of Chriſts righteouſneſs. And by <hi>eye-ſalve,</hi> we are to underſtand
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44418:11"/> the illumination of the ſpirit, even that wiſdom that cometh from above. All theſe we are counſelled to buy of Jeſus Chriſt: * yet here is no gap opened to let in Popiſh merit: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chriſtus eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ille qui merces ſalutis caelitus venales nobis promittit, et offert in Evangelio, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pretio, vel meritis paran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>precibus &amp; fide gratis Deo accipiendas. Hoc monopolium eſt Chriſti, extra quod nulla eſt ſalus,</hi> Pareus.</note> Here is not the leaſt allowance given to that rotten Doctrine of Merits: For all graces which we have, and all gifts which we have, are gratuitouſly given us by God, and to him alone we muſt aſcribe the praiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of all. Whoever then hath received this great and excellent grace of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Poverty, the free gift of God (which is by our Saviour mentioned the firſt, and leads the van to the reſt of all the Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes) he is obliged more and more daily to ſearch his heart thoroughly, and ſo to find out, and be ſenſible of, his own loſt, forlorn, and utterly undone condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as in himſelf, and ſo likewiſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend his abſolute neceſſity of make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſure of his intereſt in Chriſt; who was for this very purpoſe ſent into the world, <hi>to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt:</hi> For <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 11.</note> he profeſſeth, <hi>Matth 15. 24. I am not ſent, but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> He then, who is ſo poor in ſpirit, and vile, and deſpicable, and altogether leſs then nothing in his own eies, O!
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44418:12"/> what haſt doth he make unto Chriſt. As poor men flock apace to the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, to receive Alms, ſo all ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poor Chriſtians make haſt unto Chriſt, who only can enrich them with never fading <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iches. They therefore apply themſelves unto Chriſt, and apply his merits unto themſelves. They are tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly apprehenſive of their abſolute neceſſity of getting a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, and that without him, they are utterly undone, wherefore with all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they run to Chriſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey lay hold on him by faith (for he is their life) and they will not let go their hold.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Further, whoſoever tis endowed with this rare and pretious grace of Spiritual Poverty, he, I ſay, exerciſeth himſelf in a frequent and ſerious medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the promiſes of the Goſpel, and he applies them particularly for his own ſingular conſolation. He likewiſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditates of, and with all thankfulneſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of, the invitations of the Goſpel, and he makes particular application of them unto his own ſonl. He is one of thoſe <hi>who labors and is heavy laden,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he goes to Chriſt for reſt: For ſo runs the Invitation, and promiſe, both made by Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 11. 29. Come unto</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:44418:12"/> 
                  <hi>me all ye that labor, and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>imo delaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſati dicuntar qui ſub pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum gravi ſenſu animo faitſcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t.</hi> Beza.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Refocillatio, quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit in gratuit â peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum remiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ione ſeta eſt quae nos tranquillat,</hi> Calvin.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> But ſome are conſcious to themſelves of ſo much unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſe, as they are afraid to come, leaſt if they do come, they be utterly rejected: But O! Chriſtian, labour to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of thy unworthineſs, and mourn for the ſame, and then, notwithſtanding thy unworthineſs, be not diſcouraged; O! do not ſlacken thy pace, but make haſt to go to Jeſus Chriſt, for he hath made a gracious promiſe,—<hi>And him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>to me I will no wiſe caſt out,</hi> Joh 6. 37. Although you are poor and indigent, blind, miſerable and naked, and can claim no merit from any thing, no not the beſt things, which you can do, yet you muſt not exclude your ſelves, and ſo refuſe that great ſalvation offered to you in the Goſpel. The expoſtulation is pathetical, <hi>Heb. 23. How ſhall we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, if we neglect ſo great ſalvation?</hi> If you are thirſty, and vehemently deſire <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tam pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peres quam divites fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s graciae De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> recipit, ac largiter po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat,</hi> Muſc. <hi>in Loc.</hi>
                  </note> Chriſt, you have many ſpecial invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: One is <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſaiah 55. 1. Ha every one that thirſteth, come unto the witers,</hi> and let not want and penury ſet a barr againſt your coming, for it followeth, <hi>And he that hath no money, come ye, buy and eat,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:44418:13"/> 
                  <hi>yea come buy Wine, and Milk without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and without price.</hi> Another Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is made by Chriſt amongſt a great confluence of people.—<hi>In the laſt day, that great day of the feaſt, Jeſus stood, and cryed ſaying, if any man thirſt let him come unto me and drink.</hi> Joh. 7. 37. A Third Invitation is <hi>Rev. 22. 17. And the Spirit, and the Bride ſay, come, and let him, that is athirſt come, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will let him take of the water of life.</hi> Now leaſt any may affix a falſe gloſs, and a corrupt ſenſe upon thoſe Invitations, as if they laid down a ground for <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liberum facio cuilibet veniendi: neminem ex—cludo, prorſus omnes veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſubeo. Omnes venite &amp; accipite aquas. Domino <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t gloria.</hi> Bulling.</note> 
                  <hi>Free-will:</hi> I anſwer, That all thoſe Invitations abundantly manifeſt the <hi>Free grace of God</hi> and aſcribe nothing to mans Free will (which if we truſt to it, will prove an Aegyptian reed to deceive us.) We read Ezrah. 1. 5. <hi>Then roſe the cheif of the Fathers of Judah, and Benjamin, and the Prieſts and the Levites, with all them, whoſe ſpirit God had raiſed to go up, to build the houſe of the Lord in Jeruſalem.</hi> Before we can come to Chriſt and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Goſpel Invitation, God raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up our hearts: For ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Joh. 6. 44. <hi>No man can come to me except the Father, which hath ſent m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> draw him.</hi> But when he draws us w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:44418:13"/> can run (as the ſpouſe profeſſeth) Can. 1. 4. <hi>Draw me, we will run after the.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can run the waies of Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, he inlargeth our hearts. So ſaith the Pſalmiſt. Pſal. 119. 32. <hi>I will run the way of thy Commandments: When thou ſhalt enlarge my heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. He that is poor in ſpirit is weak, ſick, and in a diſtreſſed condition, as to his own apprehenſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of neceſſity (all delaies being laid aſide) he muſt repair to Chriſt, and beg ſtrength, health, Comforts, even all from him, as the only skilfull Phyſitian who alone can Work an effectual cure. And Chriſt is the only Phyſitian, and his blood is the only Medicine; and both the Phyſitian, and his Medicine are of infinite dignity, price, value. For no Phyſitian, nor no Medicine can work that cure, which Chriſt works, Pſal. 103. 3. <hi>For he pardoneth all iniquities, and healeth all diſeaſes.</hi> Chriſt prepares and preſcribes the Medicine: our Duty is to apply it to our wounds: For the moſt Soveraign Medicine cures not in preparation, but in Application. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt imitate the Apoſtle, by making a particular Application of of Chriſt and all his merits unto our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44418:14"/> own ſouls. For (ſaith he) Gal. 2. 20. <hi>I am cruciſied with Chriſt, nevertheleſs I live, yet not I, but Christ liveth in me, and the life with I now live in the Fleſh, I live by the faith of the Son of God, who loved me, and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve himſelf for me.</hi> After Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas had a demonſtrative Conviction of Chriſt's perſonal appearance after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, he made uſe of a Pronoun Poſſeſſive to his comfort, ſaying, Joh. 20. 28. <hi>My Lord, and my God.</hi> Whoever he be, that is ſo <hi>poor in ſpirit</hi> as to be nothing and leſs then nothing in his own accompt and value Chriſt above all, and (as the Apoſtle phraſeth <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eſt Chriſtus (ſeſe ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet uniens re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>atis eoſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> regenerans) omnia, ſcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet ad ſalutem neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria: Omnibus, ni mirum fidelibus ſanctificatis &amp; Chriſto copulatis, Eſt illis omnia meritoriè.</hi> Daven. in Loc.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Macar. Hom. 16.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> it) Col. 3. 11. <hi>All in All,</hi> he (queſtionleſs) is in the ſtate of bleſſedneſs; for (ſaith our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Matth. 5. 3.) <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in ſpirit, for theirs is the Kingdome of heaven.</hi> Obſerve how low the Foundation is laid, even in <hi>Poverty of ſpirit:</hi> But Chriſt ſetts a high Roof and glorious ſuperſtructure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo low a Foundation, even <hi>the Kingdome of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44418:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Concerning the higheſt priceing and valueing of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Second Character of a ſincere Heart <note place="margin">Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter 2. The higheſt priſeing and valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Jeſus Chriſt.</note> is to ſet the higheſt Price, Value and Eſtimation upon Jeſus Chriſt. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> This is an infallible Sign of a true Beleiver, whoſe heart is upright with God, to Price, Value, Eſteem, and Preferr Chriſt in our judgments, and affections before all the Riches of the World in their greateſt Eſtate, and confluence. This the Apoſtle ſets down as an infallible Sign of a true Believer, 1 Pet. 2. 7. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you therefore which believe he is preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> O! how high an Eſtimation did the Love-ſick Spouſe diſcover concerning Jeſus Chriſt: For (ſaid ſhe) Cant. 5. 10. <hi>My beloved is white and ruddy, the cheif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jeſus Chriſtus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſuavis eſt, totus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubris eſt, totus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lis, totus deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſecuadn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſponſae Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derabilis.</hi> Beza.</note> 
                  <hi>among ten thouſand.</hi> Chriſt is <hi>white</hi> by his innocency, purity, and immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late righteouſneſs, but he is <hi>ruddy</hi> by reaſon of his bloody ſufferings, and the effuſion of his pretious blood. To which the Prophet Iſaiah alludes in a lofty piece of Retorick Eſa. 63. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Who is this that cometh from Edom? with died Garments from Bozrah?</hi> This is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:44418:15"/> to be underſtood of Chriſt, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear <note place="margin">Loquitur Eccleſia &amp; Chriſtum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur. Quare veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes tuae ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidae ſunt? <hi>Piſcator, in Loc.</hi>
                  </note> more evidently by what followes, viz: <hi>This that is glorious in his apparell, travelling in the greatneſs of his ſtrength, I that ſpeak in righteouſneſs, mighty to ſave. Wherefore art thou red in apparrell and thy garments like him, that treadeth the wine fat?</hi> This ſcripture repreſents the meritorious ſufferings of Chriſt, in pouring out his moſt pretious blood out of his veins. His body was pierced with a Spear, <hi>and forthwith came thereout</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 19. 34. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19 13 Amictus cruentus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ab hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſtrage <hi>Parae.</hi> Tinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um non pio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ut Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma ſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piorum <hi>Grot.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>blood and water.</hi> St. John in the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation gives us a farther Evidence—<hi>And he was cloathed with a veſture dipt in blood and his name is called the word of God.</hi> Oh! what an ineſtimable value ſhould we have of Chriſt, who bought us, and paid for the purchaſe the greateſt price that ever was paid, even the price of his innocent, meritorious, and moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood. The Apoſtle obſerves the Doctrine, and injoyns us to make parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular application thereof—<hi>For</hi> (ſaith <note place="margin">Haec cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monet cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus quam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum eſſe Deo. <hi>Calv. Ezek. 34. 29. Hag. 2. 7.</hi>
                  </note> he) 1 Cor. 6. 20. <hi>Ye are bought with a price, therefore glorify God in your body, and in your ſpirit, which are Gods.</hi> Chriſt is called by the Prophet Ezekiel <hi>a Plant of renown.</hi> Chriſt is called by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Haggai <hi>The Deſire of all Nations,</hi> and by Malachy <hi>The Angel of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:44418:15"/> and by Zachary <hi>the Branch of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 1. Zech. 3. 8. Dan. 9. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and by Daniel <hi>The Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah.</hi> Add farther, by way of Singularity and excellency and incomparable Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, Chriſt is call'd our <hi>Advocate</hi> and <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Propitiation,</hi> our <hi>Redeemer</hi> and <hi>only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator.</hi> Job. 19. 25. Chriſt hath <hi>trodd the wine preſs alone.</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 5. There is <note place="margin">Iſa. 63. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>none other given under heaven, whereby we muſt be ſaved, but by the name of Jeſus. Act.</hi> 4. 11. 12. Chriſt therefore as he is of infinite value and dignity in himſelf, ſo we ought to have the higheſt eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, and to preferr him both in judgment and affections, before all the Kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them. Chriſt is compared <hi>to a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> which is beyond compare with any <note place="margin">Zech. 13. 1.</note> other, for it is <hi>a Fountain opened to the Houſe of David and to the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem for ſin, and for uncleanneſs.</hi> Chriſt is likewiſe compared to a Stone, and to ſuch a one as excelleth others in admirable Properties. Iſai. 28. 16. <hi>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold I lay in Zion for a Foundation, a Stone, a tryed Stone, a pretious corner Stone, a ſure Foundation: He that believeth, ſhall not make haſt.</hi> Farther Chriſt is compared <hi>to the Pearle of great Price.</hi> Matth. 13. 45. 46. <hi>Again the Kingdome of heaven
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44418:16"/> is like unto a Merchant man ſeeking good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 13. 45, 46.</note> 
                  <hi>Pearls, who when he had found one Pear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of great price, he went, and ſold all that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had and bought it.</hi> Whatever we eſtee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> highly of, muſt go for Chriſt, <hi>the Pearl o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Price:</hi> If we poſſeſs Chriſt in our hearts b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith, we are enriched with that poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is infinitely more worth the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the poſſeſſions of the Vniverſe. Muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> value is ſet upon the Eaſtern, and Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern treaſures of the Indies, and grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pains is taken to get them: <hi>Impiger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremos currit Mercator ad Indos.</hi> Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are not worth the nameing, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Riches of Chriſt. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowledg of Chriſt is the moſt inriching knowledge, for <hi>Col</hi> 2. 3. In him are hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">O Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris omnibus opulentior notitia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti.</note> 
                  <hi>all the treaſures of Wiſdom and Knowledge</hi> Whoſoever hath a ſaving Intereſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, is richer then the greateſt Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who is ignorant of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> And hereunto, Where there i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a high valuation of Chriſt in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Judgment, there will of neceſſity follow ardency &amp; ſtrength of affection toward <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2 Cor. 5. 14.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, conſtringit, cohibet (i. e.) totos poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ac regit, ut ejus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flatu quaſi correpti a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. <hi>Beza.</hi>
                  </note> Jeſus Chriſt. The apprehenſion of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> exceeding great love of Chriſt to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould <hi>constrain</hi> us to love him with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal love. Love is the Loadſtone o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> love, and love will never be paid, nor b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contented and ſatisfied, but with its own
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44418:16"/> coyn; I mean love, anſwering love. And the greateſt love which we can expreſs to Jeſus Chriſt, is only the reflection of thoſe Beams, which he firſt darted upon us. Whatever love we manifeſt towards God is only the Return of that love, which he firſt <hi>ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt, which is given unto us.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 5. 1 Joh. 4. 19.</note> We (ſaith the Apoſtle) love him, <hi>becauſe he firſt loved us.</hi> Where Chriſt is highly priſed, that ſoul is inflam'd with ardent love to him. Neither is this an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and common, but an extraordinary, and ſpecial love. This love is in the higheſt degree above the apprehenſion of Philoſophers. They tell us, That there is <hi>Calor ad octo,</hi> and this is in <hi>gradu intenſo, &amp; non in gradu remiſſo.</hi> Somthing that expreſſion repreſents, but we'l ſet forth the vehemency of Love in the Scripture Phraſe: Love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. 4. is hotter then <hi>the coals of Juniper;</hi> and to ſuch an extenſive heat, ſo that <hi>Cant.</hi> 8. 7. <hi>many waters cannot quench love, neither can the floods drown it.</hi> But as for all thoſe who love not the Lord Jeſus, they are curſed in this world, and in the world to come: For (ſaith the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Read</hi> Pynk <hi>in</hi> Loc.</note> 16. 22, <hi>If any man love not the Lord Jeſus Christ, let him be Anathama Maranatha.</hi> An <hi>Anathama</hi> alone is a dreadful Curſe,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44418:17"/> but that's not all, there is a <hi>Maranath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Maran-Domiaus, Athan-ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit Marana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha extrema &amp; ultima ſpecies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis quae Ebraeis Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matha di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur.</hi> Druſ.</note> added to the <hi>Anathema;</hi> and this <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranatha</hi> is reſerved until the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt to judgment, and oh! how dreadful muſt their condition be at that great and terrible day, <hi>who love not the Lord Jeſus Christ!</hi> Againſt them Chriſt will pronounce that dreadful ſentence of condemnation, <hi>Depart from me ye curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into everlaſting fire, prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Angels.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP III. <hi>A heart in love with holineſs, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced in a holy life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, is a Character of a ſincere Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Third Character of Sincerity, is a <note place="margin">Character Third. A heart in love with holineſs. </note> Heart in love with holineſs: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> For when the Heart is emptied of all ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and ſelf-confidence, and made throughly ſenſible of its own vileneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wretchedneſs, then Chriſt is highly valued and entirely loved, and cordially embraced and delighted in. Every true
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44418:17"/> Believer loves holineſs for it ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the image of <hi>God.</hi> And (as <hi>Bucer</hi> us'd to ſay) where there is <hi>Aliquid Chriſti</hi> (i. e.) any impreſſion of the image of Chriſt, there we ought to place our love. Wherefore the Apoſtle gives a ſtrict <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 23. 24. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Command—<hi>Be renewed in the ſpirit of your mind. And that ye put on the new man, which after the image of God is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in righteouſneſs and true holineſs.</hi> Where this image of God is, (which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in righteouſneſs and true holineſs) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sanctitas veritatis eſt vera ſincera minime fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata</hi> Drus. <hi>Tali inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia &amp; ſanctitate qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſint in eſse non in videri</hi> Grot.</note> it is ſtampt upon the heart, and is viſible in the life, and there is ſuch a tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent beauty, purity, and excellency, and amiableneſs in all the waies of holineſs, as the leaſt glimpſe of them are abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient to delight, rejoyce and raviſh the ſoul of every true believer. What <hi>plato</hi> ſaid of Moral vertue, much more may be ſaid of Theological vertue (i. e.) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Si Virtus &amp; humanis ocutis poſsit cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile (ſui) deſiderium excitaret-</hi>Plato.</note> Soul-ſaving grace, and holineſs, <hi>that if it could be diſcerned by Corporal eyes, it would raiſe the heart to a wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereof.</hi> Oh! how did <hi>David</hi> love the Law of God! He profeſt that Gods Law was <hi>his Delight,</hi> and that Pſal. 119. 77. <hi>he loved the commandments above Gold, yea above fine gold.</hi> Pſal. 119. 127. <hi>Thy Teſtimonies</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have taken</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 111.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>n Heritage for ever, for they are the</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:44418:18"/> 
                  <hi>rejoycing of my heart.</hi> O! What ſweet neſs did <hi>David</hi> ſuck out of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Lord! for (ſaith he) <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 9. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Judgments of the Lord are true, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous altogether: More to be deſired ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they then Gold yea then much fine Gold ſweeter alſo then honey, and the hone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> comb.</hi> There is a great reward in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> very work of holineſs: For it follows i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the next words—<hi>Moreover by them, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thy Servant warned: and in keeping o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them, there is</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Utilitas non mediocris, ſedingens ſequitur, etiamſi illi reſpectum retributio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis alicujus non habeant ſed ſimplici ac ſincer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in viâ mandatorum Dei currant, unum hoc ſpectantes, ut Domino Deo ſuo gratificentur <hi>Muſc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>great reward</hi> Now to love God for himſelfe and the Law of God for it felf and holineſs for holineſs ſake becauſe it is the image of God and reſembles him, this is a good ſign indeed that the heart is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere with God. But to profeſs religion for ſelfe and ſiniſter ends, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make a good Market to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by ingratiating themſelves with ſome Profeſſors for advantage ſake, this is a very bad Sign, and comes farr ſhort of a heart right with God. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ideo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit ut aliud magis quam ipſum aſse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatur, non Deum colit ſed illud colit quod concupiſeit.</hi> Auguſt.</note> So the Siche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites Embraced circumciſion upon a Politick deſign, to compaſs to themſelves all the Eſtate of the Iſraelites Gen. 34. 25. <note n="*" place="margin">Si vere hoc dicunt, tyran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ide baud dubie, &amp; per vim cum illis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere ſpecie foederis ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, quod vellent vi eorum bonae accipere. Ita cum doloſe cum illis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent juſte ſunt pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alioqui prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtuprum illataus. <hi>Merc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Shall not their Cattle, and their ſubſtance, and every beast of theirs be ours, only le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> us conſent unto them, and they will dwell</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:44418:18"/> 
                  <hi>with us.</hi> But that Politick, and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ended propoſall did not proſper with the Sichemites, for we read immediatly after of their utter deſtruction: No more will any men thrive in the cloſe of all, who ſeek their own ends and deſign onely ſelf-Intereſts. The People followed Chriſt for the loaves, and many like the Perſians worſhip the riſing Sun, and ſeek only their own private ends, and ſome have two faces under one hood, and ſome imitate Water men rowing upon the Thames, who look one way and row another. The Apoſtles Cenſure is veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of multitudes—<hi>For all ſeek their</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 221.</note> 
                  <hi>own, not the things which are Jeſus Chriſts:</hi> But ſuch mens hearts are not upright with God.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Ad hereunto, wherever true holineſs is ſeated in the heart, it becomes exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fruitfull in the life, and appears ſo by thoſe good fruits viſible in a holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. Not bare leaves, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal profeſſions will ſerve the turn, but there are required good actions. Chriſt muſt not only be in the tongue, to ſpeak good of his name (which is our duty;) but he muſt be formed in us, and our hearts muſt be raviſhed with love to him, and Love muſt conſtrain us to yeeld ready &amp;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44418:19"/> cheerfull obedience to him. Not only a form but the power of godlineſs muſt exert and evidence it ſelf in a Sanctified converſation. The Apoſtle cautions us againſt ſuch, who content themſelves with a bare outſide-form of godlyneſs, <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 5.</note> and deny the power thereof—<hi>Having a form of godlineſs, but deny the power thereof: from ſuch turn away.</hi> There muſt not be only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a formall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: But there muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a transforming, Rom 12. 2. <hi>We muſt be transſormed by the renewing of our minds.</hi> Queſtionleſs, where the heart is ſincere towards God, there profeſſion and practice concur in a ſweet harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and where the profeſſion is in ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ty, a holy life gives abundant Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony thereunto: For we muſt <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn the Doctrine of God</hi> (as the Apoſtle <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 10.</note> ſpeaks) and then we <hi>adorn the Doctrine of God</hi> when we evidence the ſincerity of our profeſſion by the holineſs of our lives and converſations: For wherever holineſs is in ſincerity, and in truth, it is very diffuſive, and diſcovers it ſelfe in its vaſt extent, and latitude. It conſiſts not only in verbal profeſſions, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al actions, nor is confined to one or to two acts, nor to a few particulars, but it is in the Habit, and extends it ſelfe to all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44418:19"/> manner of Converſation (as the Apoſtle <note place="margin">1 Per. 1. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Heb. 12. 14, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Per ſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſtudio enitimiai.</hi>
                  </note> exhorts) <hi>But as he that hath called you, is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi> We muſt with all diligence purſue holyneſs (for ſo the Original im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports) It is uſed of Hunters and Hounds, who follow the game, and take great pains in the purſuit thereof. Peace and Holyneſs are conjoyn'd by the Apoſtle—<hi>Follow peace with all men and holyneſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> Holy perſons, and they only ſhall be made partakers of the bleſſed Viſion: And they are thus diſtinguiſhed from hypocrites by our Saviour—<hi>Bleſſed are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> They are ſaid to be pure in oppoſition to <note place="margin">Deum jam vide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t lumine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae, quae eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſumma ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo. <hi>Spanhem.</hi>
                  </note> all manner of impurity, and profaneneſs, and pure in heart in oppoſition to all manner of hypocriſie. Whoever then hath hope to be made like unto God in happineſs, in the higheſt Heaven, muſt be firſt made like unto God in holineſs here on Earth. For holyneſs and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs differr not ſubſtantially, but gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually: For Holineſs is happineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choate in this World, and happineſs is holineſs perfected and conſummated in the World to come. Let us take a narrow View View of the Words of the Apoſtle—<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now are we the Sons of God, and it</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 2.</note>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:44418:20"/> 
                  <hi>doth not yet appear, what we ſhall be; But</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Non ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titate tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſed ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitate &amp; beatitudine, ac ſic multo magis filii ejas quam nunc. <hi>Grot.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>we know, that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him, for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> Now for the right Interpretation of thoſe words, we muſt interpoſe this Caution by way of Diſtinction—There is <hi>ſicut ſimilitudinis</hi> to be underſtood, <hi>non ſicut proportionis.</hi> In variety of places in Holy Scripture, we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <note place="margin">Lev. 11. 44. Lev. 19. 2. Lev. 20. 1 Pet. 1. 16.</note> to <hi>be holy, as God is holy;</hi> yet we muſt know and acknowledge, that it's altogether impoſſible for us poor finite Creatures to attain to that equality of holineſs, which is in God: However it is our obliged duty to endeavour accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our utmoſt ability, after a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and conformity to God. Similitudes are in the Predicament of Quality, and according to Quality, we are ſaid to be like, or unlike. But ſimilitudes are not in the Predicament of Quantity: for it's altogether impoſſible for any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to be equal and hold any propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of holineſs, with the Infinite, and Everlaſting Creator. But what's the Grand Duty incumbent on all thoſe, who hope to be partakers of the bleſſed Viſion. The Apoſtle makes mention—<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>And every one that hath this hope in him, purifieth himſelf, even as he is pure:</hi> Both outward and inward purity; holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44418:20"/> of Heart, as well as Holineſs of life are eſſentially requiſite to a good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Both Hands and Hearts (as St. <hi>James</hi> commands) muſt be cleanſed, and <note place="margin">I am. 4. 8.</note> purifyed—<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>clean perſons can have no commerce with God: If you would have a holy life you muſt get a clean heart <hi>v D. Manton in Lo. 2 Cor. 7. 1.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. In divino. Cultu nihi mutilu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed omnia abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luta eſse de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. <hi>Calv.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cleanſe your hands ye Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and purify your hearts, ye double minded.</hi> Not only outward impurity of the Body, but inward impurity of the Heart, not only practical uncleanneſs, but ſpeculative uncleanneſs ſhould be utterly abhorred, and abandoned alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: For ſo runs the Charge of the Apoſtle—<hi>Having therefore theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> (dearly beloved) <hi>let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God.</hi> This then is an undoubted Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion conſonant to the Rule of the word. That where holineſs is cordially em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced, loved, deſired, and delighted in, and rightly priced in the Judgment, and preferrd as the true Wiſdome, before Rubies and all manner of pretious Stones, and where holineſs is practiced in the life and Converſation, queſtionleſs that heart is upright and ſincere towards God, notwithſtanding many perſonal Infirmities (which we grieve for and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of) while we are in this Vale of miſery.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:44418:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII. <hi>Of ingenuous Sorrow for Sin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Fourth Character of Sincerity is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genous <note place="margin">Charact. 4. Ingenous ſorrow for our Sias.</note> ſorrow for all Sin. This E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithete <hi>Ingenuous,</hi> I therefore name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would lay down hereby a diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating note between that ſorrow; which is for the Sin, and that which is onely for the puniſhment.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> That ſorrow I call ingenuous which is for the Sin, more then for the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and this is a Filial kind of ſorrow, That I call ſervile and diſingenous, which is more for the Puniſhment, then for the Sin. A Child of God under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands the nature of Sin, as to it's filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, guiltineſs and puniſhment, which is the conſequent thereof, and therefore he laies Sin to heart, and is grieved and vexed at the very heart, becauſe God is thereby diſhonoured and his holy Law is broken. A Godly mourner mourns for Sin as it is Sin, becauſe of its filthineſs, and defilement, and becauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44418:21"/> it diſpleaſeth the only Holy Lord God, and is odious and abominable in his ſight. The Eye of every upright man affects his Heart, and melts him into Tears of Godly ſorrow, and works an inward compunction, and a heart break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſorrow. And this is that ſorrow, which is of the right ſtamp, a genuine and ingenuous kind of ſorrow. And where ever this ingenuous ſorrow is, it may be fully evidenced by ſeven Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical characters mentioned by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: For, <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>this ſelf ſame thing, that ye ſorrowed after a godly ſort, what carefulneſs it wrought in you? yea, what clearing of your ſelves? yea, what indignation? yea, what fear? yea, what vehement deſire? yea, what zeal? yea, what revenge?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> There is a very great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the mournings of <hi>Cain, Pharaoh, Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Judas,</hi> (who only mourned and roared for the ſmart of puniſhment) and the mournings of <hi>David, Paul, Peter,</hi> and <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> who mourned for their ſins; and therefore grieved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they diſpleaſed ſo good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a Lord God. For inſtance, <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> often cried out, that the plagues inflicted on him and on his people might be taken away; but what plagues did
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44418:22"/> he mean? I anſwer; he meant only the plagues of Frogs, Locuſts, Caterpillars, <hi>&amp;c. Pharaoh</hi> had a plague incumbent on him worſe than all thoſe, and that was the plague of a hard heart; of this plague he makes not any mention at all. A hard heart was his great ſin, and it was inflicted upon him as a very great judgment: But <hi>David</hi> cries out againſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 4.</note> himſelf for <hi>his</hi> ſins, and makes a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular acknowledgment: <hi>Against thee, thee only have I ſinned, and done this evil in thy ſight.</hi> And he prayes, <hi>Hide thy face</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 9.</note> 
                  <hi>from my ſins, and blot out all my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</hi> Ahab was a meer ſtranger to the Grace of <hi>Humility,</hi> and unacquainted with it altogether; yet it's ſaid of him, that <hi>he humbled himſelf:</hi> and for his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward humiliation the judgment threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned was adjourned. <hi>Seeſt thou how</hi> Ahab <note place="margin">1 Kings 21. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>humbleth himſelf before me? Becauſe he humbleth himſelf before me, I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Poenitentia ductus ſed quae non permanſit. Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid tamen de commeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ poenâ ob hoc detractum eſt. <hi>Grot.</hi> Exemplum bonitatis Dei: quatenus <hi>Achab</hi> quantumvis hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticè poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itentiam agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti poenas meritas differt. Hinc colligi pot eſt Deum, multo magis beneficum fore erga cos qui veram &amp; ſeriam poenitentiam egerint. <hi>Piſcat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>will not bring the evil in his dayes; but in his ſons dayes will I bring the evil upon his houſe.</hi> Yet of <hi>Ahab</hi> it may be more properly ſaid, that he was <hi>rather humbled than humble;</hi> for the fear and horror ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of thoſe dreadful judgments which were to be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44418:22"/> poured down againſt himſelf, and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebel</hi> his Wife, and his Poſterity, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted from him an outward humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which conſiſted in putting on Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, in faſting and going ſoftly, and looking with a ſorrowful and dejected countenance, yet all this while he had not one dram of true godly ſorrow, and of true humility. How ſad muſt be the condition of many looſe Profeſſors now a-dayes, who come ſhort of ſuch as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> was? and how dreadful muſt their condition be who come ſhort of thoſe who come ſhort of Heaven? But St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a man of another ſpirit, he was not only humbled, but humble, and had the gift and grace of true humility; and he was a true Penitent, a ſincere Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, and a godly Mourner for ſin; and he was ſo low and debaſed in his own eyes, as to account himſelf <hi>the chief of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinners.</hi> We read of <hi>Ahab's</hi> forwardneſs in offering himſelf a Voluntier and Slave to ſin, ſo that this foul Brand of Infamy is ſtampt upon him. <hi>But there was none</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Kings 21. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>like unto</hi> Ahab, <hi>which did ſell himſelf to work wickedneſs in the ſight of the Lord, whom</hi> Jezebel <hi>his Wife ſtirred up. Ahab</hi> was active, and put himſelf forward to work all manner of miſchief; he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated himſelf, without fear or wit,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44418:23"/> into any deſperate Adventure. He ſtuck at nothing, but ran on in a wild and mad career, following all ſorts of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs with a full bent, propenſion and vergency of his ſoul, and with delight and complacency, driving a Trade for Sin, and for the Devil. We read of ſuch who were almoſt ſtarved for hunger, that <hi>they flew upon the ſpoil.</hi> And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 32.</note> the Apoſtle ſtigmatizeth the vileſt of ſinners after this manner; <hi>Who being paſt feeling, have given themſelves over</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>unto laſciviouſneſs, to work all uncleanneſs with greedineſs.</hi> Of this brand was <hi>Ahab.</hi> But on the contrary, St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcovers a better ſpirit, as appears by his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation; <hi>I delight in the Law of God after</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>the inward man.</hi> He was paſſive, and with great grief and remorſe of heart <note place="margin">Tom. 7. 14.</note> complains, that he <hi>was ſold under ſin.</hi> He diſcover'd great renitency, reluctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and antipathies againſt every ſin; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that which I do, I allow not; for what I would do, that do I not; but</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>what I hate, that do I.</hi> O how did this holy Apoſtle fight and ſtruggle, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe continual Combats and Conflicts, fighting againſt Sin and Satan! And thereupon he breaks forth into a dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful complaint; <hi>But I ſee another Law in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 23.</note> 
                  <hi>my members, warring against the Law of</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:44418:23"/> 
                  <hi>my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the Law of ſin which is in my members.</hi> And it's obſervable, that all this while, and amidſt all thoſe ſad complaints, <hi>Paul</hi> was a regenerate man; and a pregnant demonſtration we have of our aſſertion, becauſe <hi>he delighted in the Law of God, For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I delight in the Law of God</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 22. <hi>Totus homo mento &amp; ratione re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur: ab ca itaque Apoſtolo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo totus appellatur,</hi> Bucer.</note> 
                  <hi>after the inward man.</hi> And to delight in the Law of God in the inward man, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be appropriated to any, but to ſuch only who are in the ſtate of Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. And that the words of the Apoſtle are not by a figure, called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it's evident that he ſpeaks in his own, and not in another perſon, becauſe he ſaith, <hi>I my ſelf.</hi> And that the Apoſtle <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 25.</note> gives no allowance to himſelf <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Idem ego vel ipſe ego, quod à</hi> Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo <hi>emphaticè dictum eſt ad deſignandum ſeipſum ne quis eum ſub alienâ perſonâ hactenus fuiſſe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutum ſuſpicaretur.</hi> Eſtius in Loc. <hi>Accipiamus hoc in ſuâ ipſius perſonâ pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuliſſe Apoſtolum.</hi> Zege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus. <hi>Hac exceptione fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur ſe it a eſſe Deo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictum, ut reptans in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tis ſordibus inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur.</hi> Calr.</note> in any ſin is clear, becauſe he profeſſeth, <hi>For the good that I would, I do not; but the evil which I would not, that I do.</hi> And the Apoſtle was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of his own impotency and inſufficiency, to extricate himſelf out of thoſe ſtraits and difficulties wherein he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved, and therefore he cries out for a deliverer, as appears in that pathetical exclamation: <hi>O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that I am, who ſhall deliver me</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:44418:24"/> 
                  <hi>from the Body of Sin?</hi> By the Body o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sin, he underſtands all ſorts of Sin, both Original and Actual, both the Roor and Fruit; the corrupt Fountain, and the corrupt Streams. And none but God ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deliver and ſet him free from them. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alone can deliver him, <hi>who delivers u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from the wrath to come,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Moreover, we are farther to conſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that there is a vaſt and a wide difference between the howling of Dogs, and the crying of Children; and there is as muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> difference between the roaring of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlaves, and the crying of godly Mourners. Wicked men, Slaves, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as feel the preſent ſmart of the laſh, cry out bitterly by reaſon of the great pain which they feel, and thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſmarting blows which they groan under.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Poe lit eat te quod tot &amp; tantis flagitiis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volutus in luto faecis &amp; miſeriae diutius ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiſti, poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tiam agens cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus tuum conteras &amp; furibunde carnis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſello iacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina ſubtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hens,</hi> &amp;c. Bern. <hi>p.</hi> 331.</note> But as for all thoſe who are true and unfeigned Mourners in <hi>Zion,</hi> they are deeply affected with godly ſorrow fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſin; and therefore they grieve and mourn, becauſe they have been ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted as to kick a tender Father upon his Bowels; and have been ſo unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as to ſin againſt riches of mercy and loving kindneſs: Hence comes thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heart-piercing, Heart-breaking, and Soul-melting Sorrows, becauſe they have been ſuch undutiful Children, as to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44418:24"/> bel againſt a gracious and merciful God, the Father of all mercies, and the God of all conſolations. No maſſie great Mountain, no not the burthen of <hi>Aetna</hi> (as the Proverb is) no weight imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or expreſſible, can be ſo heavy, as is the burthen of ſin to a Child of God. And no manner of ſorrow can be ſo bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to a godly man, as is the ſenſe of Sin, and ſorrow for it. Nothing in the World can be ſo grievous, vexing, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing, and every way afflictive to a good Chriſtian, as Sin is: for Sin to him is like a Dagger ſticking in his Heart, and continually tormenting and putting him to pain. Hereupon we read of <hi>David</hi> watering his Couch with his Tears; <hi>For</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 6, 7.</note> (ſaith he) <hi>I am weary with my groaning; I make my Bed to ſwim, I water my Couch with my Tears: Mine eye is conſumed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of grief.</hi> Further he expreſſeth an addition to his mourning, becauſe <hi>his</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>tears was his meat day and night.</hi> To eat the bread of affliction, and to drink the water of affliction is a ſad calamity, but to feed on tears muſt needs be much ſadder; but this is not all, for the Pſalmiſt confeſſeth further; <hi>There is no</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 38. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſoundneſs in my fleſh, becauſe of thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; neither is there any rest in my bones, becauſe of my ſin.</hi> Diſeaſes, aches, pains,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44418:25"/> and broken bones are very grievous <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Omnium eſt utiliſsimum dolorem corporis ex morbo vel ulcere loco peccati ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, &amp; peceati eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vocabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: ita vel hoc pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtationem peccatorum, &amp; horro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceremur.</hi> Muſc. in Loc.</note> but ſin is, or ſhould be, more grievou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to us than all. <hi>David</hi> was of a ſanguin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> complexion (and ſuch naturally are more chearful.) <hi>David</hi> was a great and potent King, and an excellent Muſician<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yet the ſenſe of his ſins cauſed great ſorrows to him, and made him go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mourning all the day long. If then the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thorow ſenſe of ſin, and the guilt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be ſet home upon the Conſcience, there will be weeping and mourning: The eye will affect the heart, and cauſe inward compunction, and godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. Thus we read of <hi>Ephraim ſmiting upon his thigh.</hi> Of <hi>Ephraim's</hi> Converſion and Repentance (which is the Fruit of Converſion) the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> makes mention: I <hi>have ſurely heard</hi> Ephraim <note place="margin">Jer. 31. 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>bemoaning himſelf thus; Thou haſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed me, and I was chaſtiſed, as a Bullock unaccuſtomed to the yoke. Turn thou me, and I ſhall be turned; for thou art the Lord my God. Surely after that I was turned, I repented; and after that I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my thing. I was aſhamed, yea even confounded; becauſe I did bear the reproach of my youth.</hi> We ſhall likewiſe find the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zek. 21. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ſighing to the breaking of his loyns.</hi> And <note place="margin">Job 42. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Job abhorring himſelf, and repenting in</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:44418:25"/> 
                  <hi>duſt and aſhes.</hi> Many mourn for worldly loſſes, and ſhed many a tear for any loſs which befals them in their temporal eſtate; but few there are which mourn for ſin, which produceth the greateſt loſs, even the loſs of God's favor. Many have cauſe to repent for their worldly mournings, and to mourn for their mournings. See the vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween worldly and godly ſorrow, 2 <hi>Cor. 7. 10. For godly ſorrow worketh repentance to ſalvation, not to be repented of; but the ſorrow of the world worketh death.</hi> If we could mourn for ſin much more, and for the world leſs, we ſhould lead more comfortable lives for the future, than ever we have formerly done.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of Sorrowing and Mourning for others Sins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> A Fifth Character of a ſincere Heart <note place="margin">Charact. 5. Mourning for others Sins. 1.</note> is Sorrowing and Mourning for others Sins. A true godly Mourner, (whoſe heart is upright with God) doth not confine and terminate his ſorrow within the narrow compaſs of his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reſt, and not let it extend any further,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44418:26"/> but he laies to heart, and unfeignedly mourns for the ſins of others. Though (as it's commonly ſaid) Charity begins at home, yet it muſt not end there; there muſt be a <hi>plus ultrà</hi> for our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; it muſt be diffuſive, and extended to others. And this is a great ſign of love, when we are aſſected with, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected for the ſins o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> others, as well as for our own. Every good man is not only grieved for his own ſins, but for the ſins of others. Of this excellent temper was <hi>David,</hi> the man after God's own heart; who from his heart pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, <hi>Rivers of tears run down mine eyes, becauſe they keep not thy Law,</hi> Pſal. 119. 136. But many there are whoſe moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Qui ſpiritu Dei agun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hi ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt tales dolorum ſtimulos, ut</hi> Loth <hi>cum videret ſceleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium collu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viem reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> &amp;c. Mollcrus.</note> are excentrick to that good man; for they are ſo far ſtrangers to mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for other mens ſins, as they make their ſins a matter of ſport, mirth and mockery: However, they would be loath to be branded for fools, yet they cannot eſcape <hi>Solomon's</hi> cenſure, <hi>Prov. 14. 9. Fools make a mock at ſin.</hi> When men make ſin a matter of pleaſure and jeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and make that a matter of laughter, which ſhould be a cauſe of mourning, they ſhew themſelves to be notorious fools. Many there are who deſervedly may be rank'd amongſt the chiefeſt and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44418:26"/> worſt ſort of fools, who when they ſee men drunk, or hear them ſwear or curſe, or talk laſciviouſly, and belch out ſuch words as (even the Heathen could ſay) <hi>corrupt good manners,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 33. then <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Menan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> thoſe men are tranſported with laughter and merriment, and they talk with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and complacency, pleaſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the remembrance of others ſins. Theſe have <hi>Solomon's</hi> brand for fools; and their folly will appear to their ſhame, when they ſhall mourn for their laughter, and weep for their wicked pleaſure and jollities. When ſome wrote Books in a jeſting and deriding manner, concerning ſeveral faults of great men, after Mr. <hi>Greenham,</hi> a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend and Learned Divine, had read thoſe Books, he was much offended at them, ſaying, <hi>That ſins ought to be made</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">V. Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams works.</note> 
                  <hi>odious, and not onely made ridiculous.</hi> Whatever ſins we either diſcern in our ſelves, or in any other, we ought to mourn for them, and not to make a ſport of them. A good Chriſtian, who is acquainted with the pangs of the New Birth, and is ſenſible of that great fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and abomination that is in every ſin, and that every ſin grieveth and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, and is odious and abominable in his ſight, ſuch a man (I ſay) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44418:27"/> he finds ſin, he hates it, and mourns for it; and therefore he is not an idle Spectator, or over-curious Inquiſitor, but a real Mourner for other mens ſins. And whilſt he mourns for others ſins, he reflects upon himſelf as a perſon made of the ſame mould, and one of the ſame paſſions, and having the ſame corrupt nature. That excellent Father St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> makes mention of an old man, who when he had heard that one of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren had committed a ſcandalous ſin, he wept bitterly, ſaying, <hi>He ſin'd to day,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Bern.</hi> in Feſt. St. <hi>Martini.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I may ſin to morrow.</hi> We are all <hi>by nature children of wrath, as others,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 3. Nature makes no difference between us and the vileſt of men: Who art thou then that boaſteſt of a good nature, and a ſweet diſpoſition? though theſe things are very commendable amongſt men, and much to be deſired, yet there's much more required; for the beſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without ſanctifying grace, is no better than poyſon in a golden Cup. Hath then God endowed thee with a greater meaſure of grace than thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? remember that it is thy duty to acknowledg with all thankfulneſs, that what grace thou haſt, is the free gift of God. <hi>And what hast thou which thou hast not received? now if thou didst receive</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44418:27"/> 
                  <hi>it, why dost thou glory as if thou hadst not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>received it?</hi> Not the goodneſs of thy nature, but the free grace of God makes thee to differ from thy Brother. O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with all thankfulneſs acknowledg God's reſtraining grace, and ſanctifying grace, whereby thou kept from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with others into the ſame exceſs of riot. All ſorts of grace come from God; as antecedent, concomitant, and ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; and a Chriſtian hath need of them all, that ſo he may begin any good work, proceed, and perſevere therein. If the Lord ſhould leave thee to thy ſelf, and let thee be fill'd with thy own ways, and give thee up to thy own hearts luſts, thou wilt quickly deſtroy thy ſelf, by breaking out into ſuch horrid ſins, as the vileſt of men give themſelves to commit with delight and complacency. It was a good Prayer in an ancient Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, <hi>Lord, deliver me from my ſelf.</hi> That rare Father St. <hi>Bernard</hi> prayed, <hi>Lord, deliver me from the evil man,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ipe me a malo homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, a me i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi> Bern. <hi>de i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter. Dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſelf.</hi> Thus he counted himſelf the evil man, and thus he diſcovered ſingular humility.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Let's not neglect our duty, in being both affected with, and afflicted for the ſins of others, as remembring, that we are men of like paſſions; and we are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44418:28"/> duſt and aſhes, frail creatures, our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers being <hi>Amorites,</hi> and our Mothers <hi>Hittites;</hi> notwithſtanding we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd from the commiſſion of many ſins which others ordinarily commit, we have great cauſe of thankfulneſs, but not the leaſt cauſe of being proud. If through riches of mercy we have hopes of a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt, (we not knowing the ſecret Decree of God) for ought we know others may be fellow members of Chriſt's Body, and fellow Citizens of the new <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> we ought therefore to ſympathize with them, and be alike affected with variety of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations towards them, as the Apoſtle commands, <hi>Rom. 12. 15 Rejoyce with them that do rejoyce, weep with them that weep.</hi> For any one to ſay as <hi>Cain, Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> What am I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in anothers matters? let every one look to himſelf: ſuch ſpeeches as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>elare ſcriptum eſt a</hi> Platone <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on a nobis ſolum nati ſumus, ſed ortus noſtri partem pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria, partem pareates ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dicant, partem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici.</hi> Cic. <hi>off. lib.</hi> 1.</note> theſe are ſo far below a Chriſtian ſpirit, as they come ſhort of a moral Heathen: For one of the beſt of Heathen Orators cites <hi>Plato,</hi> (and commends his ſaying) <hi>We are not only born for our ſelves, but our Country, our Parents; our Friends challenge a part of us.</hi> And Sympathies and Antipathies are critical Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and diſcriminate Friends from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44418:28"/> Enemies. If then our Brethren be in adverſity, then we ſhould mourn with them; if they be in proſperity, we ſhould rejoyce with them. <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3. 11. that <hi>God hath made eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing beautiful in his time, alſo he hath ſet the world in their heart.</hi> And that ſhews the beauty of Providence; for God hath abundantly diſcovered his beautiful ordering of all the affairs of the World, repreſenting his infinite Wiſdom and gracious Providence. Now ſeaſons of Providence are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and we ought to act according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; as the ſame Wiſe man exhorts, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 7. 14. In the day of proſperity be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but in the day of adverſity conſider: God alſo hath ſet the one over against the other, to the end that man ſhould find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing after him.</hi> And as we ought to take notice of Providences in general, ſo we ſhould take notice of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conditions of others, as conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all things come by a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, either permitting or approving. No ſin is approved of, but altogether abhorred by Almighty God; yet God permits that which he approves not of. For the greateſt of ſins which the Jews committed, in embrewing their hands in the blood of Chriſt, came to paſs by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44418:29"/> Divine permiſſive Providence; (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake <hi>Acts 2. 23.) Him being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by the determinate counſel and foreknowledg of God, ye have taken, and by w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cked hands have crucified and ſlain.</hi> That which was an Act of the higheſt Malice in the Jews, was an Act of great Providence in God.</p>
               <p>Wherefore though we cannot (though if we could we ought) prevent and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the commiſſion of ſins in others, yet (be they never ſo bad) we ought hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to mourn for them. So did <hi>Lot</hi> mourn for the abomination of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites;</hi> though they were ripe for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, by reaſon of their exceeding great wickedneſs, (as if they had attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the higheſt degree of ſinning) yet <hi>Lot</hi> grieved and mourned for them, who no way grieved nor mourned for themſelves. Of <hi>Lot's</hi> mourning for thoſe wicked <hi>Sodomites,</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſets an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial remark, 2 <hi>Pet. 2. 7. And delivered just</hi> Lot, <hi>vexed with the filthy converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wicked.</hi> The word imports more then an ordinary ſorrow and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Significas opprimi, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigari, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ter aſſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi.</hi> Gerh. in Loc.</note> for their wickedneſs, for it ſignifies to be oppreſſed, wearied, and grievouſly afflicted. And it's further added; <hi>For that righteous man dwelling among them, in ſeeing and hearing, vexed his righteous</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:44418:29"/> 
                  <hi>ſoul from day to day with their unlawful deeds,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 8. And here is another word expreſſing a greater grief or vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The word implies a ſifting and ſearching; ſo in <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophanes,</hi> &amp; others note upon the word: So that many have been queſtion'd by ſuch ſearching and torturing to force confeſſion. 2. The word ſignifieth to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Rev. 14. 10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> vex, rack and torment; and it expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the torments of Hell. <hi>Lot</hi> was as it were upon the rack, and for the time imagin'd himſelf to be ſo tormented in his Soul, as if he was in Hell, by ſeeing and hearing thoſe abominations of the <hi>Sodomites.</hi> And as <hi>Lot,</hi> ſo the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> was a true Mourner for the ſins of others; he wept abundantly for the dreadful judgments inflicted on the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites: his Rhetorick is rais'd to a high pitch. <hi>My bowels, my bowels; I am pained at my very heart; my heart maketh a noiſe in me, I cannot hold my peace; becauſe thou hast heard, O my Soul, the ſound of the Trumpet, the alarm of War,</hi> Jer. 4. 19. And he ſtrains himſelf to a higher piece of Rhetorick, <hi>Jer. 9. 1. O that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the ſlain of the daughter of my people.</hi> But he not only weeps for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44418:30"/> the judgments, but in an eſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for their ſins, <hi>Jer. 13. 17. But if ye will not hear it, my Soul ſhall weep in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret places for your pride.</hi> By what hath been mention'd, let's utterly deteſt the careleſs, heedleſs temper of <hi>Cain, Gallio, &amp;c.</hi> and let us look upon our ſelves concerned, not only to mourn for, and bewail our own ſins, but mourn for, and bewail the ſins of others alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Shewing, that all ſincere-hearted Chriſtians labour to approve their Hearts towards God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> THE ſixth Character of a ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted <note place="margin">Charact. 6. A ſincere heart ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it ſelf. </note>. Chriſtian, is to approve himſelf to God, and to put himſelf in the integrity of his heart upon the teſt, trial and examination of God himſelf, who only knows the heart, and alone can ſearch it thorowly. Thus <hi>David</hi> durſt not ſtand upon his own ſearching, but caſts himſelf altogether upon God's ſearch and trial: <hi>Judg me,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>O Lord, for I have walked in mine integrity;</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:44418:30"/> 
                  <hi>I have truſted alſo in the Lord, therefore I ſhall not ſlide. Examine me, O Lord, and prove me; try my reins and my heart,</hi> Pſal. 26. 1, 2. Likewiſe in another Pſalm <hi>David</hi> puts himſelf upon a farther teſt and trial, <hi>Pſalm 139. 23, 24. Search me, O God, and know my heart; try me, and know my thoughts. And ſee if there be any wicked way in me, and lead me in the way everlaſting. Job</hi> makes his appeals and applications unto God alone. <hi>Behold,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my witneſs is in Heaven, and my record is on high,</hi> Job 16. 19. Hence he diſcover'd a reſolution truly heroical. <hi>I will not remove my integrity from me. My righteouſneſs I hold fast, and will not let it go: my heart ſhall not reproach me ſo long as I live,</hi> Job 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5, 6. Variety of the fouleſt ſlanders are caſt upon the people of God, (as Hiſtories mention) even ſuch lies and calumnies were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, as bad as the Father of lies could invent. <hi>Nero,</hi> when <hi>Rome</hi> was burnt, imputed the burning of it to the Chriſtians; and the Romiſh Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Traytors (had their Treaſon took effect) were reſolved to have laid the whole Treaſon upon ſuch whom they maliciouſly ſtigmatized with the nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name of Puritans. It's an old Policy (though there is not one dram of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44418:31"/> in it) of <hi>Machiavel;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">To accuſe <note place="margin">Auducter criminare aliquid hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebit.</note> boldly, and caſt dirt enough, hoping that ſome may ſtick on.</q> Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, all thoſe whoſe hearts are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and upright towards God, do raiſe to themſelves a ground of ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, from the teſtimony of a good conſcience; that notwithſtanding hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane infirmities, the whole frame, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, and reſolution of their hearts is, to walk in the fear of God all the day long. The Apoſtle ſpeaks in his own name, and in the names of all upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Chriſtians, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 12. For our rejoycing is this, the teſtimony of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that in ſimplicity, and godly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, not with fleſhly wiſdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World, and more abundantly to you-wards.</hi> Wherefore then we muſt make it our grand ſtudy and buſineſs to approve our hearts to God, and alwaies to walk as in the preſence of God, as having the fear of God before our eyes; if ſo, amidſt troubles, trials, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, we may take abundant comfort in the integrity of our hearts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> It muſt be daily bewail'd (what we cannot deny) that we are ſubject to many infirmities, and ſhall never be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44418:31"/> quite exempted from them whilſt we are in this World, yet if we groan under the burthen of them, and mourn for them, and pray and ſtrive againſt them; there may be ſincerity in the heart, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding human infirmities incident to our lives. We read in that Parable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 5. that all the Virgins ſlept, even the five wiſe Virgins as well as the five fooliſh Virgins: <hi>While the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom tarried, they all ſlumbred and ſlept.</hi> That ſleeping implies infirmity. Both wiſe and fooliſh <hi>went forth to meet the Bridegroom,</hi> verſe 1. <hi>Both of them took their Lamps,</hi> verſe 3. <hi>But the wiſe took oyl in their Veſſels, with their Lamps; i. e.</hi> they had grace in their hearts. Both wiſe and fooliſh had the Lamps of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned judgment, and of an <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Per oleum unde lampa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des aluntur ne exting ua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur poterit exponi cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis juſtitia, ſinceritas &amp; vigilantia, quae eſt in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ ſolida, &amp; perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti fide Chriſti, &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate non ficta. Nam ſine tali corde, quid aliud eſt quicquid foris oſtenditur, quam lampas quaedam adſque oleo.</hi> Muſc. in Loc.</note> outward profeſſion; but the wiſe had made proviſion for ſupplies, and augmentation of all the graces of the ſpirit of God. Thoſe five wiſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, notwithſtanding they ſlept as well as the fooliſh, yet they were admitted to the Marriage, when the fooliſh loſt the ſeaſon, and a door of hope was for ever ſhut againſt them. For we read <hi>Matth. 25. 10. And while they went to</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:44418:32"/> 
                  <hi>buy, the Bridegroom came, and they that were ready went in with him to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and the door was ſhut.</hi> The Spouſe likewiſe had her infirmities, and ſhe was ſenſible of them, ſo ſhe profeſſeth, <hi>Cant. 5. 2. I ſleep, but my heart waketh.</hi> She confeſt (as ſome have obſerv'd) <q rend="margQuotes">That ſecurity had oppreſt her in a great <note place="margin">Vid. Engliſh Annotat.</note> meaſure; but yet the inward bent and motion of her heart was active and vigilant.</q> Let us, Oh! let us ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this Fort-Royal of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; this is a better defence than a wall of Braſs. Bulwarks and Forts have <note place="margin">Hic murus abeneus eſto Nil conſcire ſibi nullâ palleſcere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulpâ.</note> been took by ſtratagems, or by ſtorm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; great Caſtles built upon Rocks may be undermind, and the ſtrongeſt Military Garriſon may be forced to yield, leſt they be ſtarved: but a good Conſcience cannot be ſtarv'd, for it's <hi>a continual feast. Ahaſhueroſh</hi> made a magnificent Feaſt unto the common People <hi>ſeven daies,</hi> but <hi>unto his Princes and Nobles, an hundred and fourſcore daies,</hi> Eſther 1. 4, 5. But he that daily keeps a good Conſcience, he keeps a Feaſt every day. And notwithſtanding many aſſaults and batteries, a good Conſcience will be a ſhield of defence, and as a Bulwark impregnable, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from the malice and miſchief
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44418:32"/> of unreaſonable and malicious Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. However men may be inraged againſt us, and accuſe us falſly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us unjuſtly, yet if a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience acquit us, we have more to make for us, than all accuſations and condemnations of the worſt of Enemies can make againſt us. Wherefore we ſhould make it our continual endeavor to walk with that wiſdom and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, as we may put to ſilence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men, who watch for our haltings, and would gladly make us an offender for a word. And a good Conſcience, and a good Converſation, will make our Enemies to be aſhamed. <hi>Having a</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Christiant teſtatum mundo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerent, ſe procul ab omni impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, verae<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> pietatis corruptela ab eſſe, quo nomine im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecti e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</hi> Calv.</note> 
                  <hi>good conſcience, that whereas they ſpeak evil of you, as of evil doers, they may be aſhamed that faſly accuſe your good conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 16. Here is the great labour, and the great work, ſo to endeavor to order our hearts and our lives, that we may amidſt all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and calamities, either imminent or incumbent on us, appeal to God, the ſearcher of all hearts, whoſe curious eyes are more then ten thouſand times ten thouſand, even infinitely more bright than the Sun in his brightneſs; before whom all things are tranſparent; to whom day and night are all one; the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44418:33"/> darkeſt night hideth not from God: For (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 13.) <hi>neither</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Tradunt Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>dici quae a collo ſuſpenſa excorian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; per dorſi ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem reſupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata fia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur ut tota ſoris &amp; intus oculis pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant.</hi> Beza.</note> 
                  <hi>is there any creature that is not manifeſt in his ſighi; but all things are naked and opened unto the eyes of him with whom we have to do.</hi> If then the Queſtion (which is a very material one) be askt, What is that which will carry us through the greateſt ſufferings? I anſwer, that a God reconciled in Jeſus Chriſt, a Conſcience pacified, and a Righteous Cauſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> when we ſuffer for Righteouſneſs ſake, will make us Conquerors, and more than Conquerors, as the <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8. 37. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſupervinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in eruce etiam gloriamur, nedum ut, animam deſpondeamus.</hi> Cypr-Epiſt. 26.</note> word very emphatically imports, mentioned by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 8. 37. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincimus. Nay, in all theſe things we are more than Conquerors, through him that loved us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:44418:33"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Where the Heart is ſincere, there will be a preſſing forward towards Perfection.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> I Proceed to a ſeventh Character of a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charact. 7. A preſsing forward towards Perfection.</hi>
                  </note> ſincere Heart; and this both an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Character, and an Apoſtolical Practice; <hi>viz.</hi> A preſſing forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Perfection. St. <hi>Paul</hi> propounds his own Example as a Pattern for our imitation, and what he had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and known to be good expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally, he communicates to us, and exhorts to reduce into practice. <hi>Not as</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>though I had already attained, either were already perfect, but I follow after, that I may apprehend that for which alſo I am apprehended of Christ. Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehended, but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are before; I preſs toward the mark for the price of the high calling of God in Christ Jeſus: Let us therefore, as many as be perfect be thus minded,</hi> Phil. 3. 12, 13, 14, 15. This
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44418:34"/> progreſſive motion <hi>David</hi> laies dowor is a ſign of ſuch who are bleſſed, <hi>Pſal. 84. 6, 7. Who paſſing through the valley of</hi> Baca <hi>make it a well, the rain alſo filleth the pool: They go from ſtrength to ſtrength, every one of them in</hi> Zion <hi>appeareth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</hi> Their indeavors are indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable, and their motions are continued and progreſſive in the ſervice of God. Hence judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerves upon the place; <q rend="margQuotes">That the faithful recollect <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ae ſi dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt fideles collectis ſubiade vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ad moatem</hi> Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>nec laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitudiae ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lâ tardari, donec con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicia at Dei faciem.</hi> Calv in Pſal. 84. verſ. 7.</note> their ſtrength, and aſcend unto the mount of <hi>Zion,</hi> and are not hindred by any wearineſs till they behold the face of God.</q> Our grand indeavor ſhould be to get grace, and truth of grace; and to be diligent in ſearching whether we have got ſpecial and more than common grace; and whether we miſtake not parts for graces. We muſt ſtill be ſitting, examining, and trying whether our grace be true and genuine, ſincere and ſaving grace: And our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor muſt be continued to get growth in grace, and more acceſſions thereunto. If we would be preſerved from apoſtacy and back-ſliding, we muſt grow in grace; for growth in grace is a ſpecial preſervative to keep us from falling from our ſtedfaſtneſs. For ſo ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 17, 18. Ye therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44418:34"/> ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware, leſt ye alſo being led away with the error of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs.</hi> A ſovereign remedy to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the danger of Apoſtacy, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the following words, <hi>verſ. 18. But grow in grace, and in the knowledg of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A growing Believer is a new born Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <hi>As new born babes deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 2. Likewiſe augmentation of every particular grace is required: We muſt labour for true grace as to the quality of it; and as to the quantity of it we muſt ſtill be adding thereunto. So ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 5, 6, 7, 8. Add to your faith virtue, and to virtue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſt inſignis hic locus, ſi quis alius verae Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae vitae ſummam, deſcriptis illius ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris tum cruſis tum effectis ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctandam praebens.</hi> Beza.</note> 
                  <hi>knowledg, and to knowledg temperance, and to temperance patience, and to patience godlineſs, and to godlineſs brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to brotherly kindneſs charity: For if thoſe things be in you, and abound, they make you that ye ſhall neither be bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren nor unfruitful in the the knowledg of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> We have need of every grace; and the more we have of any grace in ſincerity and in truth, the more we ſhall value it, and the more we ſhall beg ſupplies of God, and increaſe from him. The Apoſtles pray'd, <hi>Lord,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:44418:35"/> 
                  <hi>increaſe our Faith.</hi> If we have any grace already really wrought in us, we ſhall be ſenſible what need we have of, and ſhall pray for, a continual augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> To inſtance in particulars: Have we faith? let's fift narrowly, and examine thorowly, whether our faith be a ſaving faith; whether it be <hi>a juſtifying faith,</hi> Rom. 5. 1. ſuch as <hi>works by love,</hi> Gal. 5. 6. and <hi>purifies the heart,</hi> Acts 15. 9. (for this only is of the right ſtamp:) or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our faith be only hiſtorical, dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical, and only temporary. If we ſearch exactly, upon mature and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate reflections upon our ſelves, we ſhall find ſome failings and deficiencies in our faith: For though (queſtionleſs) the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> had true faith, yet <hi>they had ſomething lacking in their faith.</hi> And yet they were ſuch for whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle gave thanks to God in an eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (i. e.) <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris fidem veſtram aa huc imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectam ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvamus.</hi> Beze in Loc.</note> manner, <hi>1 Theſ. 3. 9, 10. For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>what thanks can we render again to God for you, for all the joy wherewith we joy for your ſakes before our God night and and day, praying exceedingly that we might ſee your face, and perfect that which is lacking in your faith?</hi> And as we ſhould labour for more faith, ſo ſhould we labour for more love, more meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44418:35"/> more humility, and more ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial. If then through the pride of our own hearts we ſhould flatter our ſelves as if we had grace enough already, it's evident that we never had any grace at all in ſincerity and in truth; for where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever true grace is planted in the heart, it fructifies in the life and converſation. Grace is no withered dead plant, but a living and growing plant; where the ſeed of grace is ſound in the heart, it takes root downward, and brings forth fruit upward throughout the practice of our whole lives. <q rend="margQuotes">He then who la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Qui deſinit proſicere, incipit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere.</hi> Bern.</note> not to grow better, begins to grow worſe, as a Father ſaith.</q> Though covetouſneſs, and a greedy carking care after the World are unlawful, yet here is a lawful covetouſneſs; for to deſire more grace is a holy covetouſneſs. To be <hi>rapax &amp; tenax,</hi> i. e. to get get and graſp all that one get, and not to be willing to part with any thing, are characters of covetous Earth-worms; but to be eager <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Stadium exigit &amp; majorem quandam in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dis ſoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualibus cupiditale.</hi> Theoph.</note> and greedy after increaſe of every grace, and when we have got grace, to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the utmoſt to keep it, this is the only lawful kind of covetouſneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13. <hi>Covet earneſtly the beſt gifts.</hi> And grace is the beſt gift, Chriſt himſelf only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:44418:36"/> Gifts of Tongues, and gifts of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are highly to be valued, but this gift of Grace is of far greater value. Grace is <hi>Quid conſtitutivum;</hi> i. e. that which conſtitutes a true Chriſtian. Though Tongues, and Arts and Sciences are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in their kind, yet many bad men may have them, and many good men may want them; but Grace is of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity, for without it we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come to Heaven; and <hi>without holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs we ſhall never ſee the Lord.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us cry out for Grace, as <hi>Solomon</hi> makes mention of <hi>the Horſleeches two Daughters, Give, give,</hi> Prov. 30. 15. Wherefore we ſhould not reſt ſatisfied &amp; contented with theſe meaſures of Grace whereunto we have at preſent attained, but we ſhould make it our great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſtudy, and indeavor to grow from one degree of grace unto another: We muſt no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> only <hi>follow holineſs,</hi> Heb. 12. 14. but <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7. 1. We muſt ſtrive after per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of grace; though we are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed with many imperfections in this World, yet we muſt not allow our ſelves in them, but mourn for them; and ſtill go on in adding grace to grace here, till at length grace be ſwallowed up in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44418:36"/> glory; and we then ſhall attain to the end of our hope, the ſalvation of our immortal Souls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Shewing, that where the Heart is ſincere, there is a ſtrict Watch ſet upon the Heart and Life, to keep us from boſome Sins.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe eighth Character of ſincerity is a <note place="margin">Charact. 8. A ſtrict Watch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> ſtrict Watch ſet upon the Heart and Life, againſt all and every boſome and beloved Sin: Be thy ſins as dear and as near as a right hand, or a right eye, they muſt be cut off, and pluckt out; for ſo ſaith our Saviour, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſervem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s in hac Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti admonitione quo ſerio qno fervore quamque ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementi cautione opus ſit regnum Dei quaere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ibus ut offendiculorum occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones undicunq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e irruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes amputent.</hi> Muſch. in Loc.</note> 
                  <hi>Matth. 5. 29, 30. And if thy right eye offend thee, pluck it out, and caſt it from thee; for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members ſhould periſh, and not that thy whole body ſhould be caſt into Hell. And if thy right hand offend thee, cut it off, and caſt it from thee; for it is profitable for thee that one</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:44418:37"/> 
                  <hi>of thy members ſhould periſh, and not that thy whole body ſhould be cast into Hell.</hi> But theſe words may not be underſtood literally, of mutilating and of diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring of our ſelves, but we are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them as ſpoken by way of caution, and of ſtrict command, not only to avoid all ſins, but all manner of appearance of evil; and likewiſe all ſorts of occaſions and temptations to ſin. The Pſalmiſt gives a clear note of diſtinction between him whoſe heart is upright, and him whoſe heart is not upright towards God, <hi>Pſal. 18. 23. I was</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>upright be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Neque quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ia pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſiudio perget, niſi qui ſedulo ſe cuſtodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ab iai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>itatc ſua.</hi> Caiv. in Loc. <hi>Ab iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate meâ,</hi> i. c. <hi>ad quam natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meâ proius ſum,</hi> h. e. <hi>ne quid pravi ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milterem aut neſcc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terem quas antea ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſiſſem.</hi> Vatabl.</note> 
                  <hi>him, and I kept my ſelf from mine iniquity.</hi> It's plain and evident from that Scripture, that every boſome ſin, which <hi>David</hi> calls <hi>mine iniquity,</hi> ought in an eſpecial manner to be watched againſt, and prevented; and if we be overtaken with it, we ſhould loathe and leave it. That ſin is a boſome ſin which is <hi>peccatum in deliciis,</hi> a darling ſin, like a <hi>Delilah</hi> in the boſome; an <hi>Agag,</hi> a ruling ſin; a <hi>Gibeonite,</hi> a pretending ſin: any ſin that pleads <hi>with an Exceptive,</hi> as <hi>Naaman</hi> did, 2 <hi>Kings 5. 18. In this thing the Lord pardon thy Servant, that when my Maſter goeth into the houſe of</hi> Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>to worſhip there, and he leaneth on my hand, and I bow down my ſelf in the</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:44418:37"/> 
                  <hi>houſe of</hi> Rimmon, <hi>the Lord pardon thy Servant in this thing.</hi> All theſe, and ſuch like Apologies and pleadings, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and excuſes for ſin, muſt be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly abhor'd and abandon'd altogether. Suppoſe thy ſins may be leſfer compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively than ſome others, yet no ſin can be ſo little, but it's greatly hated and abhor'd by Almighty God, and deſerves his wrath to be poured down upon the Sinner unto all eternity. As for inſtance, ſuppoſe thou accuſtomeſt thy ſelf to petty and leſſer Oaths, frothy and vain diſcourſe, jeſting lyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet all theſe have filth and guilt in them, and are odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and abominable in the fight of God, and therefore we ought to deteſt and utterly forſake them. One of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers, of the higheſt rank, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his judgment, <q rend="margQuotes">That none ought <note place="margin">Auguſti</note> to tell (though but one) a lye, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the telling of that one lye might ſave the whole World.</q> The Reaſon of that Aſſertion is grounded upon that Propoſition of eternal Truth, <hi>We may not do evil that good may come thereof.</hi> Ancient ſins, which are of long ſtanding and cuſtom, ſuch as are ſins of pleaſure and profit, ſuch as ſuit moſt with the genius, complexion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of particular men, and conduce
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44418:38"/> moſt to the ſatisfaction of carnal luſts, and to the pleaſing of fleſh and blood, and corrupt nature, are ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing extenuated, as notwithſtanding Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom and Antiquity, they carry a greater Aggravation with them. Thieves, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, and ſuch notorious criminal perſons, cannot expect to fare a whit the better, but the worſe altogether, for pleading a cuſtom and habit in their wickedneſs: Wherefore then let us in good earneſt loat he and deteſt all ſins, and after loathing and deteſting, leave and forſake all manner of ſins; and break off both acts and habits of ſinning by unfeigned repentance, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to God. And let us fulfil that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie by our daily practice, <hi>Iſai. 30. 22. Ye ſhall defile alſo the covering of thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Images of Silver, and ornament of thy molten Images of Gold. Thou ſhalt cast them away as a menſtruous Cloth; thou ſhalt ſay unto it, Get thee hence.</hi> Let none preſume to plead for any ſin, as <hi>Lot</hi> pleaded for <hi>Zoar; Is it not a little one? and my Soul ſhall live.</hi> A little leak in a Ship, if it be neglected and not ſtopt up preſently, may ſink the Ship, and ſo all in the Ship may be ſuddenly drowned. A little Thief put into a Window may open the Door, and let in a multitude of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44418:38"/> ſuch deſperate Cut-throats, as may quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy a whole Family. A little Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knife, a little Aul or Bodkin, may kill a man as ſoon as either Sword, Spear, or Gun. <hi>Siſera</hi> the General of <hi>Jabin's</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ran away on his feet, and ſo eſcaped the edge of the Sword in the open field, but by <hi>Jael</hi> he was kill'd in the Tent: for we read, <hi>Judges</hi> 4. 21. That <hi>Jael,</hi> Heber's <hi>Wife, took a Nail of the Tent, and took an Hammer in her hand, and went ſoftly unto him, and ſmote the Nail into his Temples, and faſtned it into the ground, (for he was fast aſleep and weary) ſo he died.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> In our moſt compoſed and deliberate thoughts, let us conſider that there is no ſin ſo little, but (without the interpoſing of the merits of Chriſt) will damn us both Body and Soul into the nethermoſt Hell. There is no little God, no little Price paid to make an Attonement for Sin; and no little Hell, the place of Torments. Oh then! as thou conſulteſt the good of thy precious Soul, lay aſide altogether all manner of Apologies, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, pleadings, and expoſtulations, and all manner of hopes of obtaining any Diſpenſations for any one Sin, which may be comparatively leſſer than ſome others: As for that ſin which in thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44418:39"/> is not to be regarded, as if it were either a little one, or none at all, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance and pardon, purchaſed through the Bloud of Chriſt) thy Soul and Body may be caſt into that Lake which burneth with Fire and Brimſtone to all eternity. One of the chiefeſt rank of the Roman Hiſtorians relates what <hi>Hanno</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That ſuch a <note place="margin">Parvus hic ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is iace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>geis exuſcitet. <hi>Iav.</hi>
                     </note> little Spark might cauſe a great Flame.</q> The Embers of an evil Thought may ſet the whole man in combuſtion: ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thoughts which are <hi>in embrione,</hi> and not yet come to maturity, yet being not cruſh'd not diſallowed, may in a ſhort tract of time bring forth evil words, and afterwards full-born actions of all ſorts of abominations. As ſoon as <hi>Goliah,</hi> that inſolent proud-daring Champion, was brain'd, and his Head with his own Sword ſever'd from his ſhoulders, then forthwith the whole Army of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtins was routed, and utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown. If then all Champion-reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sins (ſuch I call ſo which are darling boſome Sins) be conquered and deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then all other ſins which are of more than ordinary incurſion, will the ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be vanquiſhed and ſubdued. We read that when the King of <hi>Syria</hi> went to joyn battle againſt <hi>Ahab</hi> King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:44418:39"/> 2 Kings</hi> 22. 31. that he gave ſtrict command <hi>to his thirty and two Captains, that had rule over his Chariots, ſaying, Fight neither with ſmall nor great, ſave only with the King of</hi> Iſrael. Now if the Queſtion be made, Why was the battle principally deſign'd againſt the King of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> The Anſwer is at hand, Becauſe the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was the worſt Enemy, and moſt hating, and moſt hated. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in our ſpiritual warfare we muſt valiantly encounter and fight againſt every ſin, yet in an eſpecial manner we muſt with renewed ſtrength fight againſt all boſome ſins; becauſe the more they are delighted in, and hugg'd in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, they prove more miſchievous; as Vipers and Serpents, who being once received into the boſome, ſuddenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe who give them entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Queſtionleſs every ſin is of a poiſonous and deſtructive nature; yet a beloved ſin carries with it more aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating circumſtances, and ſo proves more miſchievous and deſtructive; as may be abundantly evidenced by the ſad conſequences thereof, as daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience witneſſeth abundantly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> For a further illuſtration of the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by a plain and obvious ſimilitude: Would any man, though of an ordinary
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44418:40"/> capacity, habour Vipers, Adders, Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, Toads, and ſuch like noxious and hurtful creatures in his houſe? would any entertain ſuch kind of dangerous creatures in his bed, and lay them in his boſome, and ſo venture to ſleep with them? None can eaſily imagine that any there are who are ſo far ſequeſtred from common ſenſe and reaſon, as to venture to give a boſome reception to ſuch kind of creatures which are offenſive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive unto mankind. The chiefeſt of the Heathen Orators tells us, <q rend="margQuotes">That <note place="margin">Principio generi ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantium omni eſt a naturâ tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butum, utſe, vitam corpuſque tueatur, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elinetq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e ea, quae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citura vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deantur. <hi>Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. off. Ib. 1.</hi>
                     </note> naturally all creatures muſt defend their life and body, and avoid all thoſe things which are hurtful.</q> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let's conſider ſeriouſly, and after mature deliberation we ſhall confeſs, that any beloved Sin is worſe than any Viper, Scorpion, Adder, or Toad in the boſome; and whilſt thou embraceſt and pleaſeſt thy ſelf in any beloved Sin, thou takeſt a ready courſe to deſtroy both thy Body and Soul. Wherefore, Oh Chriſtian! if thou haſt any love, any regard or commiſeration of thy immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and heavenly-born being Soul, give not thy ſelf the leaſt allowance or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation in any beloved Sin: for if thou pleadeſt for thy Sins, thou art the greateſt Enemy to thy own Soul. Let
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44418:40"/> not any voluptuous man plead for his pleaſures and ſenſual delights; let not any unchaſte man plead for his Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, or for any wanton laſcivious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; let not any vain frothy Jeſter and Scoffer plead for any wittily contriv'd lye, colluſion, or any abuſive carriage; let not any Tradeſman excuſe his lying, and overreaching in his Trade, and vending of ſophiſticated wares, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe commodities; let him not flatter himſelf with vain pretences, as if his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, equivocating, and jugling, would much conduce to his profit; let him not pretend that he cannot keep open ſhop, and maintain his family; and if he ſhould once leave his lying, and ſwearing, and couzening, his family would be utterly undone. All ſuch kind of pleadings are odious and abominable in the ſight of God. Neither Antiquity nor Cuſtom, nor pleaſure nor profit will excuſe thee in the leaſt, nor relieve thee before the impartial Tribunal of Jeſus Chriſt: When thou ſhalt appear before the Judgment-ſeat of Chriſt, then all ſinful pleadings, and all vain Apologies, will be ſo far from extenuating or leſſening thy ſin at that great day, as that they will aggrava<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them both as to the ſilth and guilt of them. And then Chriſt
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:44418:41"/> will pronounce againſt thee that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſentence of condemnation. We read <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. that ſins of omiſſions could not in the leaſt excuſe them: And ſome in an eſpecial manner have bewail'd <hi>their ſins of omiſſion;</hi> how then ſhall the <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Uſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> late Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </note> commiſſions of ſcandalous ſins excuſe thee at that great day of account; and amongſt other ſins, ſuch as are beloved, boſome and cuſtomary ſins, moſt pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fleſh and blood; theſe will ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate both thy ſins and thy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at the day of Judgment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:44418:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>A deſire and univerſal endeavour againſt all and every Sin, is a Character of a ſincere Heart, and it's accompanied with the Practice of all Duties.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> THe ninth Character of ſincerity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charact. 9. A deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour againſt all Sins, and for the practice of all Duties.</hi>
                  </note> in a deſire univerſally extenſive, and an equal endeavour againſt all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and all ſorts of Sins, and a deſire and endeavor as extenſive to yield obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto all Command, and to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice all Duties.</p>
               <p>The deſire and endeavour muſt be <note place="margin">The deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour muſt be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive againſt all ſins.</note> extenſive againſt all manner of all ſins. There muſt be a deſire and endeavour to refrain from every evil way; and not only from one ſin, but from all ſins of all ſorts, and all manner of ſizes; though as conſidered comparatively they may not be pleaded for at all, (though leſs than others) but they muſt be utterly abandoned and forſaken, as well as others of a greater filth and guilt. Thus the Pſalmiſt profeſſeth, <hi>Pſal. 119. 101. I</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:44418:42"/> 
                  <hi>have refrained my feet from every evil way, that I may keep thy word.</hi> By feet we are to underſtand, the whole courſe of our lives and converſations in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive ſenſe, taking in the whole duty of man. And that we may <hi>keep the Word</hi> of God, and keep cloſe to his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, we muſt wage war againſt every ſin, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Significat ſe bellum indixiſſe omnibus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis, ut ſe Deo in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequium de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret.</hi> Calv.</note> 
                  <hi>refrain our feet from every evil way.</hi> There muſt then of neceſſity be an univerſal loathing, and an univerſal leaving of every ſin; for in every ſin, even in ſuch as ſome call a <hi>peccadillo,</hi> there is poiſon and venome, for which there is no other Antidote but the Bloud of Jeſus Chriſt. There is no ſin which is in its own nature venial, unleſs the Bloud of Chriſt make it ſo. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that commonly received diſtinction amongſt Papiſts, of <hi>venial</hi> and <hi>mortal ſins,</hi> is to be diſcarded altogether, as a rotten diſtinction: The Papiſts may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to their own practice, call ſins venal, becauſe they ſet ſins to ſale and grant Indulgences for money; and ſo hope to make a good Market of Peoples bad lives, thereby intending to inrich the Popes Coffers, and the Prieſts Purſes. But they in the mean time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly derogate from the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, by preſumptuouſly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44418:42"/> to themſelves a power of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving of ſins, upon the payment of moneys for Indulgences. Againſt them may be juſtly retorted the ſame cenſure which the Apoſtle pronounced againſt <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Acts 8. 20. for offering of money: <hi>Thy money periſh with thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou hast thought that the gift of God may be purchaſed with money.</hi> As for Popiſh Pardons and Indulgences, both Givers and Takers are abominable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they undervalue the pardoning Mercy of God in Jeſus Chriſt. It's an undoubted ſign of all thoſe who love God, <hi>to hate evil.</hi> So ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 97. 10. Ye that love the Lord, hate evil.</hi> And this hatred muſt be an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal hatred of all manner of ſins, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception; and it muſt be a perfect and irreconcileable hatred. Deadly fewds (ſuch as Chronicles mention) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Family and Family, were barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and abominable, and tended to the utter ſubverſion of many Families: But here, a deadly fewd is lawful; <hi>i. e.</hi> to perpetuate our hatred and enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all manner of ſins and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>David</hi> declares his utter hatred and indignation againſt all the Enemies of God, <hi>Pſal. 139. 23, 24. I hate them, O Lord, that hate thee. And am not I</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:44418:43"/> 
                  <hi>grieved with thoſe that riſe up against thee? I hate them with a perfect hatred, I count them mine enemies. David</hi> hated their ſins rather than their perſons; though he loved their perſons, yet as they were God's enemies, for their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious rebellions againſt God, he hated them with a perfect hatred. It's an univerſal charge enjoyn'd by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 9. to all without exception, <hi>Abhor that which is evil, and cleave to that which is good.</hi> Not only one Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice, but all the breed of Cockatrices are of a poiſonous and deſtructive na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and miſchievous to mankind, and therefore not only ſuch as come to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, but thoſe alſo which are in the Egg ought to be deſtroyed. So every ſin is of a poiſonous and miſchievous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and therefore ought to be ſtifled in the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> conception, and be prevented from proceeding to any ripeneſs. For any Woman to ſtifle and deſtroy the fruit of her womb (though the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception be very early) is abominable murther in the ſight of God; and if ſuch courſes be practiſed, they tend to the rooting out a ſucceſſion of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: But as for all manner of ſins and wickedneſs, though newly committed, and gone no further then a thought, yet
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44418:43"/> that very evil thought ſhould be checkt and diſallowed. The School men have coyn'd quaint notions, and amongſt them are mention'd <hi>motus primo primi;</hi> let them not mince nor extenuate ſins by ſuch Cob-web diſtinctions; for thoſe beginnings, (to ſpeak more plainly) which by them are call'd <hi>primo primi,</hi> are ſinful; thoſe firſt riſings and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as ſinful, are to be deſtroyed, mourned for, and never ſuffered to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to any further maturity.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> 2. As there muſt be a refraining and <note place="margin">2. An en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to practiſe all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</note> abſtaining from all manner of ſins, ſo there muſt be an endeavour to obey all Commands, and practiſe all Duties. Hereupon the Pſalmiſt profeſſeth, <hi>Pſal. 119. 6. Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have reſpect unto all thy commandments.</hi> It is an infallible and undoubted ſign of a gracious heart, neither to divide in duties nor in commands; neither to make exceptions and diſtinctions, as if one grace was to be got, and not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Neither may we plead a diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation from any duty, whether it be commanded in the firſt or ſecond Table. For inſtance, whoever he be that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends a ſtrict obſervation of the Sabbath day (I mean only the Lords day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath) and pretends a hatred of ſwearing
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:44418:44"/> and lying, and of all manner of Idolatry, and yet this man is diſhoneſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt in his dealings, he is without doubt an errand Hypocrite; and likewiſe who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be that pretends to deal juſtly and uprightly between man and man, and to pay every one his own, (which is both neceſſary and commendable) and yet this man makes no conſcience at all of obſerving the Lords day, nor of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Word or Oath, nor of uſing the Name of God with reverence, ſuch a man is but a meer formaliſt, and a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the power of godlineſs: For the ſame God who commands one duty commands another, and laies an equal obligation to yield ready and chearful obedience unto both Tables. For the whole Law of God is copulative, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lex Dei eſt uta tota co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulativa.</hi> Illyric.</note> one Commandment is joyn'd to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a link of the ſame golden Chain. Hence it appears in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> Deut. 5. 18, 19, 20, 21. that there is a conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenation and connexion between all the Commandments of God. <hi>Neither ſhalt thou commit adultery, neither ſhalt thou ſteal, neither ſhalt thou bear falſe witneſs against thy neighbour, neither ſhalt thou deſire thy neighbours wife, neither ſhalt thou covet thy neighbours houſe, his field, or his man-ſervant, or his maid-ſervant,</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:44418:44"/> 
                  <hi>his ox or his aſs, or any thing that is thy neighbours.</hi> From which Scriptures we conclude, That there ought to be an equal regard unto one Commandment <note place="margin">Q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jcquid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> cum ſi, equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er ſit.</note> as well as another; for there is one only holy Lord God, who commands one Commandment in the Decalogue as well as an other. This was the very trade, or grand employment which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did drive, <hi>Acts 24. 16. To keep a conſcience void of offence, towards God and towards man.</hi> The Apoſtle did not ſhift and put off this grand negotiation from himſelf, as if he were unconcern'd, and therefore left it to others; but it's ſaid, <hi>herein do</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I exerciſe my ſelf.</hi> Neither did the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſit faſt and looſe, and (as we ſay) exerciſe himſelf by fits and ſtarts only, but he made it his buſineſs, exerciſe and imployment; for it's ſaid, <hi>alwaies.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> will any ſort of conſcience, at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſerve the turn; becauſe there are many bad conſciences: but the Apoſtle only values and exerciſeth <hi>a conſcience</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>void of offence.</hi> And ſuch a conſcience, in its extent and latitude, is a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or an infallible note of the ſincerity of that heart, which in the Apoſtles lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, <hi>keeps a conſcience void of offence, toward God and toward men.</hi> Farther the ſaid Apoſtle makes mention of three
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44418:45"/> ſignificant Adverbs, which comprehend the whole duty of man; <hi>viz. ſoberly,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>righteouſly, and godly.</hi> As to all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and to all ſorts of duties com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Word of God, we muſt make it our buſineſs to manifeſt our thorow and impartial obedience, not picking and chuſing, as if when we had perform'd an eaſier duty, then we might obtain a diſpenſation for a greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. But all ſuch manner of halving and dividing is odious and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in the ſight of Almighty God; for every divided heart is <hi>faulty,</hi> as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Hoſ. 10. 2. Their heart is divided, therefore they ſhall be found faulty.</hi> Wherefore Univerſality of the ſubject, <hi>the whole man,</hi> which in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive acceptation takes in all the members of the Body, and faculties of the Soul, Univerſality of the object, <hi>the whole Law,</hi> and Univerſality <hi>of time and place,</hi> are eſſentially requiſite to the compleating of the obedience of every ſincere hearted Chriſtian. This Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter ſearcheth very near the heart; and he who hath it, without all queſtion is a ſincere hearted man. By this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter let us in an eſpecial manner try our ſelves; even by the univerſality of our hatred of all manner of ſins, and by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44418:45"/> the univerſality of our obedience unto all God's commands; and by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of our endeavours to grow in every grace. Univerſality is both a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſive and conſtitutive difference, for it diſtinguiſheth a half nominal and formal outſide Chriſtian, from a ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; and it conſtitutes a Child of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Where the Heart is upright with God, it is without guile and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe tenth Character of ſincerity, is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charact. 10. A ſpirit without guile. Sect.</hi> 1.</note> a ſpirit without guile and hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. <hi>Nathanael</hi> had this teſtimony from Chriſt, <hi>John 1. 47. Behold an Iſraelite in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in whom is no guile.</hi> And to have a ſpirit without guile, is that grand diſtinguiſhing Character which the Pſalmiſt appropriates to a bleſſed man, <hi>Pſal. 32. 1, 2. Eleſſea is he whoſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion is forgiven, whoſe ſin is covered. Bleſſed is the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n unto whom the Lord im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth not iniquity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</hi> Who are they who are
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44418:46"/> thus bleſſed? Such whoſe ſins are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and not imputed to them. And who are they whoſe ſins are forgiven, and not imputed to them? Such in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile. Only thoſe who are pure in heart ſhall ſee God. Purity of heart is one of thoſe tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Beatitudes mention'd in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours Sermon upon the Mount, <hi>Matth. 5. 8. Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> They are ſaid to be pure, in oppoſition to profaneneſs; and pure in heart, in oppoſition to hypocriſie. They only ſhall be partakers of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Viſion, whoſe hearts are pure, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> ſincere with God. True Believers, whoſe hearts are upright, and their lives holy, they ſhall ſee ſome manifeſtations of God by his Word, and by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences; and they ſhall ſee the footſteps and out-goings of God in the Sanctuary. But what they ſee here, is but little in compariſon of what they ſhall ſee and enjoy in glory. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor. 13. 12.) we ſee through a glaſs, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but then face to face. Now I know in part, but then ſhall I know even as alſo I am known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Every upright perſon is compounded of three ſigniſicat words, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the whole duty of integrity:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:44418:46"/> And they are ſimplicity, ſingleneſs, and ſincerity.</p>
               <p>The firſt word is ſimplicity; and this <note place="margin">1. <hi>Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</hi>
                  </note> is oppoſite to a double heart, and to ſuch a heart as is uſually call'd, <hi>a heart and a heart.</hi> This ſimplicity of the heart was a ground of the Apoſtles rejoycing, and of all true Believers: For ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 12. For our rejoycing is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>this, the teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity,</hi> &amp;c. And it's the high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation aſcrib'd to the Children of <hi>Zebulun,</hi> 1 Chron. 12. 33. that <hi>they were not of a double heart.</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> ſtamps a brand of infamy upon a double minded man, in that he is <hi>unſtable in all his waies,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> James 1. 8. He is unſixt, unplaced, and ſo unſettled, as you know not what to judg of him, nor (as we uſe to ſay) where to find him: A man may as ſoon hold the wind in his hand, as hold faſt an unſtable man.</p>
               <p>A ſecond word is ſingleneſs: Now <note place="margin">2. <hi>Single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  </note> ſingleneſs and uprightneſs differ only in the ſound of the name pronounced; they agree in the ſame ſenſe altogether, as being of a ſynonimous ſignification. Of this ſingleneſs of heart we have a clear evidence of the Primitive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, <hi>Acts 2. 46. They continued daily</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>with one accord in the Temple, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44418:47"/> bread from houſe to houſe, and eat their meat with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of heart, praiſing God.</hi> It's the obſervation of judicious Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quia in laudando Deo non poteſt eſſe cordis ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitas niſi conſtet in omnibus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae partibus, ideo certum eſt ejus fieri mentionem hoc ſenſu quod fideles eain ubique colueriat.</hi> Calv. in Loc.</note> That ſimplicity of heart, and praiſing of God, are joyn'd together: And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he gives is this; <q rend="margQuotes">Becauſe in praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, there cannot be ſimplicity of heart, unleſs it conſiſt in all the parts of our lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> This ſingle and undivided heart is highly eſteem'd of in the ſight of God: Wherefore we are commanded to <hi>turn unto the Lord with all our hearts,</hi> Joel 2. 12. And the Pſalmiſt profeſſeth, <hi>Pſal. 119. 10. With my whole heart have I ſought thee: O let me not wander from thy commandments.</hi> An entire, ſingle, one heart, are all one in ſenſe; and ſuch a one only obtains acceptance in the ſight of God, the ſearcher of all hearts.</p>
               <p>A third word is <hi>godly ſincerity;</hi> ſo I <note place="margin">3. <hi>Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſite cerâ.</note> call it, becauſe it's ſo call'd by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; godly ſincerity, or the ſincerity of God. Hereby is neceſſarily to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, that we muſt not only be ſincere in all that we do towards men, but in all that we do towards God. Simplicity and godly ſincerity are joyn'd together by the Apoſtle, and they cannot be parted aſunder. The Apoſtle likewiſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44418:47"/> prays for the <hi>Philippians,</hi> Phil. 1. 10. <hi>That ye may approve things that are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that ye may be ſincere, and without offence till the day of Christ.</hi> In this place here are two ſignificant words to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; one is, <hi>ſincere:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Original, and according to the received Etymology, derived from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſol,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>judico:</hi> And this is as (moſt ſay) an alluſion to the practiſe of Eagles, who turn the faces of their young ones to look upwards towards the Sun, and if they cannot behold the Sun, they throw them down as ſpurious, and not of the breed of Eagles. Thus far this alluſion may be improved, That all our thoughts, words and actions, ſhould be ſo genuine, and ſo rightly ordered, as they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Sun of Righteouſneſs, and be approved of by Almighty God. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther word to be opened in that Text, is <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Qui inoffenſo curſu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git. Qui non poſsit offendi qui nuſquam offendat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>inoffenſive;</hi> in the Original it's <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>(i. e.)</hi> We ſhould ſo look to our ſteps as that we may not ſtumble; and we ſhould walk ſo prudently, as we may neither give nor take offence. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive walking the Apoſtle injoyns in the extent and latitude of it, 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 32. Give none offence, neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle gives in ſpecial charge
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44418:48"/> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 Cor. 6. 1. <hi>We then as workers together with him, beſeech you alſo that ye receive not the grace of God in vain.</hi> And how muſt they evidence their not receiving the grace of God in vain? He adds <hi>verſe 3. Giving no offence in any thing, that the Goſpel be not blamed.</hi> All Miniſters, in an equal manner, ought to keep up the honour of their Miniſtry, by a faithful and diligent diſcharge of their duty, and by the holineſs of their lives and converſations. Many foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd raſh Cenſurers are ſo ignorant, as not to diſtinguiſh between the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Miniſtry, and therefore blame the whole Miniſtry for the default of ſome particular Miniſters: Wherefore Miniſters and People, eſpecially ſuch as are Profeſſors of Religion, muſt labour to walk ſo unblamably, as they may (what in them lies) preſerve the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Honour of the Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. Inoffenſive and circumſpect walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is the wiſeſt walking. <hi>See</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ. 5. 15.) how circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>you walk.</hi> Not only the matter, but the manner is required; and this preciſe walking is the wiſeſt walking. <hi>Not as fools, but as wiſe.</hi> They who walk in diſſolute courſes, and live without God in the World, they are the fools,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44418:48"/> and ſo will be found to be another day: And an eſpecial effect of circumſpect wiſe walking conſiſts in redeeming of time. <hi>Redeeming the time, becauſe the daies are evil,</hi> Epheſ. 5. 10. He then whoſe heart is without guile, evidenceth it ſo to be in the integrity of his life and converſation; as a good tree is known by the good fruits which it bears. And this upright walking is the only ſure and ſafe walking; but the contrary thereof is alwaies accompanied with variety of dangers and miſchiefs: As <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov. 10. 9. He that walketh uprightly, walketh ſurely; but he that perverteth his waies ſhall be known.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:44418:49"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of Mortification of the Deeds of the Body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe eleventh Character of a ſincere <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charact. 11. Mortifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Deeds of the Body. Sect.</hi> 1.</note> Heart, is Mortification of the Deeds of the Body; <hi>i. e.</hi> all manner of Luſts, and the evil fruits of corrupt nature. Carnal luſts, and all the works of the fleſh muſt be mortified. And that we may the better know what they are, the Apoſtle gives us a large Catalogue of the works of the fleſh, <hi>Gal. 5. 19, 20, 21. Now the works of the fleſh are manifest, which are theſe; adultery, fornication, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, laſciviouſneſs, idolatry, witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, envyings, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, drunkenneſs, and ſuch like.</hi> Our duty is to confer the ſtrength of our beſt endeavours, to ſet upon the practice of mortification of all thoſe fore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and not of thoſe only, but of all other ſins: For not only one particular member, not only one particular act, not only one particular affection or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty muſt be mortified, but the habit,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:44418:49"/> nature, and conſtitution, even the whole body of ſin muſt be mortified. Every ſin muſt have a mortifying blow, and not only be left half dead, but dead alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. I have heard an obſervation made of two eminently Learned and <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Job. Reynolds,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Guil. is bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker.</hi>
                  </note> Valiant Champions of the Truth, that one of them fought ſo long with his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, that he conquer'd and ſlew him in his Diſputations; the other did not only ſlay his Adverſary, but buried him. Thus muſt we deal with every ſin; our endeavour muſt be to deſtroy all our ſins utterly, to kill and bury them, that ſo they may never riſe againſt us in this World to our ſhame, nor in the World to come to our condemnation. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we find the curſed fruits of ſin, we muſt utterly deſtroy them; neither muſt ſin only be deſtroyed in the fruits, but in the roots alſo: both root and branch muſt be pluckt up. When the plague of Leproſie was ſpread in any houſe, God gave a ſpecial command, <hi>That the Prieſt ſhould break down the houſe, and the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Levit. 14. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtones of it, and the timber thereof, and all the morter of the houſe.</hi> Sin is a ſpiritual infectious Leproſie; and wherever it is, it ought to be rooted out. The mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a Leprous houſe may not be made uſe of for daubing of any houſe; no
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44418:50"/> more may any ſin be mingled in the worſhip of God. We read of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous cruelty of <hi>Pilate,</hi> Luke 13. 1. who <hi>mingled the bloud of the Galileans with their ſacrifices.</hi> But it's moſt juſt for God to reject all our ſervices, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us, when we mingle our ſins, vain fancies, and ſinful inventions, with the purity of his worſhip. <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> are ſtanding examples and warning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces againſt offering ſtrange fire unto the Lord. And that is ſtrange fire which is after our will-worſhip, and deviſed by our own brains, and not according to divine Inſtitution. We have the Hiſtory upon record, <hi>Lev. 10. 1. And</hi> Nadab <hi>and</hi> Abihu <hi>the ſons of</hi> Aaron <hi>took either of them his cenſer, and put fire therein, and put incenſe thereon, and offered ſtrange fire before the Lord, which he commanded them not. And there went out fire from the Lord, and devoured them, and they died before the Lord.</hi> We may not offer to God the lame and the blind. <hi>And if ye offer the blind for ſacrifice, is it not evil? and if ye offer the lame and ſick, is it not evil? offer it now unto thy Governor; will he be pleaſed with thee, or accept thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 1. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaith the Lord of hoſts?</hi> As for all thoſe who put ſuch a high affront and indignity upon God, as to offer the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44418:50"/> and worſt of their ſervices, (as if they thought any good enough for him.) they incur that dreadful curſe, <hi>Mal. 1. 14. But curſed be the deceiver, who hath in his flock a male, and voweth and ſacrificeth unto the Lord a corrupt thing; for I am a great King, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, and my Name is dreadful amongst the Heathen.</hi> If then we would offer any acceptable ſacrifice unto God, we muſt mortifie our ſins and corruptions, and offer unto God the beſt of our ſervices: <hi>the male in the flock,</hi> and the beſt male.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Although the Lord commanded the ſacrifice of Bullocks and Rams, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet he rejected the ſacrifices of the Jews, and had no reſpect to their perſons, nor to their ſacrifices. Thus the Lord expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the caſe with them, <hi>Iſai. 1. 12, 13. When ye come to appear before me, who hath required this at your hand, to tread my courts?</hi> And the Lord forbids them to bring ſuch kind of ſacrifices, <hi>verſe 13. Bring no more vain oblations; incenſe is an abomination unto me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But might not they truly have replied, that <hi>incenſe, oblations, ſacrifices, &amp;c.</hi> were all of Divine inſtitution? God commanded them all, why then ſhould not they yield obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand accordingly?</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:44418:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I anſwer, They were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to offer ſacrifice; but they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſacrifice in a wrong manner: For in every ſervice which we perform to God, we ſhould do it in a right manner, and for a right end; not only the action it ſelf, but the manner of performing it muſt be regarded. The Jews reſted only in the Ceremonial ſervice, and in the multitude of external ſacrifices, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no regard at all to their own hearts and lives: theſe they ſhould have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up to God pure and holy; but their hearts were exceeding foul, and their hands were full of bloud; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God rejected both their perſons and their ſacrifices. For thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>verſe 15. When ye ſpread forth your hands, I will hide mine eyes from you; yea, when you make many prayers, I will not hear; your hands are full of bloud.</hi> Firſt then before we can offer any acceptable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto God, we muſt ſet upon the practice of mortification and ſlaughter of all our ſins. Wherefore the ſpecial charge of the Apoſtle is, <hi>Col. 3. 5. Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſie therefore your members which are upon the earth: fornication, uncleanneſs, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate affection, evil concupiſcence, and covetouſneſs, which is idolatry.</hi> Not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> luſt may be ſpared: All carnal luſts may
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44418:51"/> be compared to thoſe brats of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which are appointed for utter deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. To this purpoſe we may apply that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 137. 8, 9. O daughter of</hi> Babylon, <hi>who art to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; happy ſhall he be that rewardeth thee as thou hast rewarded us. Happy ſhall he be that taketh and daſheth thy little ones againſt the ſtones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Some make it a Queſtion, (though good Chriſtians make no Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of it at all) Whether ſelf-murther be lawful?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer: It's murther in the higheſt degree, and an apparent breach of the ſixth Commandment, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</hi> As no murther ſhould be committed againſt another, much leſs againſt a mans ſelf: But for every one of us to ſlay our ſins, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy our corruptions, is no ſelf-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for then a Chriſtian lives beſt of all, when he hath ſlain his ſins and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. We muſt make it our daily prayer, that God would deſtroy our ſins, and ſave our Souls. Every ſin we muſt account <hi>a Benhadad,</hi> deſign'd for deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Therefore <hi>Benhadad</hi> being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God for utter deſtruction, <hi>Ahab</hi> by ſparing him brought inevitable ruine upon himſelf and his people. For
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44418:52"/> thus ſaith the man of God to <hi>Ahab,</hi> by the word of the Lord, 1 <hi>Kings 20. 42. Becauſe thou hast let go out of thy hand a man whom I appointed to utter deſtruction, therefore thy life ſhall go for his life, and thy people for his people.</hi> If then we give quarter to any one ſin, and hug it in our boſomes, we take a ſpeedy courſe to deſtroy our own Souls; for by ſhewing fooliſh pity to ſpare any one ſin, we prove cruel to our precious Souls; we our ſelves being the greateſt enemies to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Farther, we muſt take ſpecial cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of ſuch ſins as either are ſecret, unknown to any man, or elſe ſuch as come not within the verge of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Law of man; as wanton and amorous glances, vain frothy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and covetouſneſs, on which God ſets a peculiar brand of infamy, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 5. and calls it <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Now Idolatry is a ſin of a high aggravation, for it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors to rob God of his honour, and to aſcribe that honour and glory to Mammon, and worldly rich men, which is only due to the eternal Creator, <hi>God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Likewiſe we muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what a wide difference the Apoſtle makes between carnal living, and the practice of mortification; the difference
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44418:52"/> is as great, as between life and death, and ſo are the different effects and iſſues of both. For ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 8. 13. Ifye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die; but if ye through the ſpirit do mortifie the deeds of the body, ye ſhall live.</hi> We read of that glorious Victory which the Lord wrought for Iſrael againſt <hi>Amalek,</hi> an inveterate enemy; after this Victory was obtained, we read that <hi>Moſes built an Altar, and called the name of it</hi> Jehovah Niſſi; <hi>for he ſaid, becauſe the Lord hath ſworn, that he will have war with</hi> Amalek <hi>from generation to generation,</hi> Exod. 17. 15, 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> The Queſtion may be askt, Why was war to be made and continued from generation to generation againſt <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lek?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Anſwer is obvious; they were cruel and bloudy Enemies, deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of all manner of mercy, and bowels of compaſſion, and therefore God char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Moſes</hi> to make a Record of this ſignal Deliverance. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>write this for a memorial in a Book, and rehearſe it in the ears of</hi> Joſhua; <hi>for I will utterly put out the remembrance of</hi> Amalek <hi>from under Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But it will be further askt, Wherein conſiſted the particular ſin of <hi>Awalek?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:44418:53"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For Anſwer, <hi>Moſes</hi> gives a full relation, <hi>Deut. 25. 17, 18, 19. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what</hi> Amalek <hi>did unto thee by the way, and ſmote the hindmost of thee, even all that were feeble behind thee, when thou wast faint; and he feared not God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall be when the Lord thy God hath given thee reſt from all thine enemies round about, in the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee for an inheritance to poſſeſs it, that thou ſhalt blot out the remembrance of</hi> Amalek <hi>from under Heaven; thou ſhalt not forget it.</hi> As war by Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be waged againſt <hi>Amalek,</hi> ſo it's the appointment of God that we ſhould continue fighting and warring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſins and corruptions. In this caſe onely it's lawful to perpetuate a deadly fewd, and remain alwaies im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable and irreconcileable againſt all our ſins; we muſt not make the leaſt peace, nor admit of any parly for peace for any ſin, though it be of long ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, cuſtom and antiquity, and pleaſing to fleſh and bloud.</p>
               <p>To what hath been mentioned, I will add for further explication two ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant words; <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of which the Apoſtle makes an empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical mention, 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 27. But I keep under my body, and bring it into ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44418:53"/> lest that by any means when I have preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt-away.</hi> The firſt word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rendred, <hi>I keep under my body:</hi> but there lies in the word a greater emphaſis; for the word ſignifies <hi>to beat the body black and blue;</hi> and further yet in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of the word, it ſignifies <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>eſt par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciet quae o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis eſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecta, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuendo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>octum, ſeu dejectu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. Beza.</hi>
                  </note> to beat under the eye, and to leave a mark there of redneſs and blueneſs. The other word is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and this properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, <hi>to bring into ſubjection:</hi> it's a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor took from Oxen, whom we bring under the yoke; or from any ſuch Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures whom we enſlave or captivate, and bring them into ſubjection, for our uſe and ſervice. We ſhould then indeavor ſo to bring down our bodies, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due them, as to make them ſerviceable to our ſouls, and ſubject and obedient to the yoke of Chriſt; if ſo, we have well learn'd the Doctrine of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A learned moral Heathen will condemn many diſſolute livers, who call themſelves Chriſtians, and yet live without God in the world: <q rend="margQuotes">I am (ſaith <hi>Seneca)</hi> greater, and born to greater things, than to be a ſlave to my body.</q> Every Drunkard is a ſlave to his Cups, and every Whoremonger a ſlave to his Harlot, and every covetous Worldling
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:44418:54"/> is a ſlave to his Mammon: But our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign muſt not be to enſlave our Souls to our Bodies; but the deſign which we drive, muſt be to make our Bodies ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to our Souls. It was an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaying of <hi>Ephrem Syrus,</hi> who flouriſht in the third Century after Chriſt; <q rend="margQuotes">He that feaſts his Body, and ſtarves his Soul, is like him that feaſts his Slave, and ſtarves his Wife.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:44418:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Vivification of the Fruits of the Spirit is a Character of a ſincere Heart.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe twelfth and laſt Character of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Charact. 12. Vivification of the fruits of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Sect.</hi> 1.</note> (which I ſhall only mention) is, The Vivification of the Fruits of the Spirit. After mortification of the deeds of the Body, there muſt neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the Vivification of the Fruits of the Spirit; for where Chriſt dwells in a Soul by faith, and by the influence of his grace, <hi>the Body is dead,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom. 8. 10.) becauſe of ſin; but the ſpirit is life, becauſe of righteouſneſs.</hi> A Learned and Judicious Writer thus interprets that Scripture; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quam vis peccatum morfi nos adjudicet quatenus in nobis remanet primae na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae vitioſibus ſpiritum tamea Dei eſſe victore noc obſtare quod tantum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiis donati ſumus quia vel una ejus ſciatilla vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ae ſemen eſt.</hi> Calv. in Loc.</note> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Although (ſaith he) ſin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns us to death, ſo far as the remainders of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, and the vitioſity thereof remains in us, yet the Spirit is Conquerour: wherefore notwithſtanding out primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive corruption, one ſpark of the Spirit
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:44418:55"/> of God is a ſeed of life to us, though in this world we receive only the firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruits thereof.</q> All thoſe who by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, can never be brought from death to life, and from the ſtate of nature into the ſtate of grace, any other way but by the quickning virtue of Jeſus Chriſt. For ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>You hath he quickned, who were dead in your treſpaſſes and ſins.</hi> Such as are now (through grace) in a ſtate of regeneracy, were in their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition in a ſtate of unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; and ſuch who are now quickned, were formerly in a dead condition: As it's ſaid of the converted Prodigal in the Parable, <hi>Luke 15. 32. He was dead, and is alive again; and was lost, and is found.</hi> The Apoſtle diſcovers the great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the ſtate of regeneracy and unregeneracy, (and the difference is great, as great as the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween life and death.) Let's diligently review the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>in time past ye walked according to the courſe of this World, according to the Prince of the power of the Air, the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: Among whom alſo we had our converſation in times past, in the luſts of our fleſh, fulfilling the deſires</hi> (or wills) <hi>of</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:44418:55"/> 
                  <hi>the fleſh, and of the mind, and were by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the children of wrath, even as others.</hi> And what is the ſole moving cauſe of all? it followeth <hi>verſ. 4, 5. But God who is rich in mercy, for his great love where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he loved us, even when we were dead in ſins, hath quickned us together with</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Sect. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt; by grace ye are ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But the Queſtion may be askt, How may ſuch who are regenerated and quickned by Chriſt, be diſtinguiſhed from ſuch who are unregenerate, and yet dead in their treſpaſſes and ſins?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer, as a tree may be known by its fruits which it bears; <hi>i. e.</hi> a good tree, by good fruits; and a bad tree, by bad fruits; ſo may regenerate be diſtinguiſhed from unregenerate: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate bring forth the fruits of the fleſh, as <hi>adultery, fornication, uncleanneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 19, 20, 21. before mentioned; but regenerate perſons bring forth the fruits of the Spirit. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives us a double Catalogue; one is ſhort, but very comprehenſive, <hi>Epheſ. 5. 9. The fruit of the ſpirit is in all goodneſs, righteouſneſs and truth.</hi> The other is a large Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, <hi>Gal. 5. 22, 23. The fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, long-ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, againſt ſuch there is no Law.</hi> If
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:44418:56"/> then the fruits of the Spirit exert and manifeſt themſelves in the holineſs of our lives and converſations, it's an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſign of our vivification by the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>By thoſe twelve forementioned Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of a ſincere Heart, we may and muſt put our ſelves upon a ſtrict ſearch and enquiry, whether our hearts be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and upright towards God? We muſt then with all diligence and impartiality make a ſtrict ſearch into our hearts; we muſt ask, <hi>What have I done?</hi> Jer. 8. 6. we muſt <hi>commune with our own hearts,</hi> Pſal. 4. 4. and (as the Church reſolves, <hi>Lam. 3. 40.) Let us ſearch and try our ways, and turn again to the Lord.</hi> And I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that if we have one of thoſe Characters forementioned in ſincerity and in truth, we have the reſt; for they are all Links of one and the ſame golden Chain, and there's ſuch a concatenation between them, as one cannot be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:44418:56"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Containing the Comforts pertaining to ſincere Chriſtians in their Lives in this World.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving laid down thoſe twelve fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Characters and Signs of Sincerity, I thence infer this Concluſion, That it's the grand Duty incumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us all, and every one in particular, to propound the Queſtion (as in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God) to his own Soul, Am I a ſincere-hearted Chriſtian, yea or no? Let us with deliberate thoughts conſider of thoſe twelve above-named Signs and Marks of Sincerity, and examine our ſelves by them accordingly: herein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the grand Labour and Work, to buſie our ſelves with all frequent and ſerious ſelf-reflections, and heart-exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations; and let us as one man, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one particularly, propound the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion (as in the preſence of God) to his own Soul, ſaving, Is my heart ſincere and upright towards God? There are many needleſs Queſtions propounded,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:44418:57"/> which gender ſtrife, and it were better that they had been buried in ſilence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together; but here is the Queſtion wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our ſtudying and ſtating, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether our hearts ſtand ſincere to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God? As for all thoſe whoſe hearts are without guile, as <hi>Nathanael</hi>'s was, <hi>John</hi> 1. 47. who have truth in the inward parts, (as God requires, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 6.) who are men after God's own heart, (as <hi>David</hi> was) whoſe hearts are perfect with God, as <hi>Hezekiah, Aſa,</hi> and <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat</hi> were, theſe notwithſtanding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities incident to human nature, ſhall find the comfort and benefit of their up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs and ſincerity in their lives, and in their deaths, and after death to all eternity.</p>
               <p>Sincere-hearted Chriſtians receive <note place="margin">Sincere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons receive comfort in their lives.</note> comfort in their lives: Although God's dear Children meet with variety of ſore and grievous afflictions in this preſent World, and encounter with many ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and great troubles and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, inſomuch as they are the very <hi>Butt</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> againſt which their implacable Enemies ſhoot their keeneſt and ſharpeſt Arrows, poiſoned and deſtructive: yet notwithſtanding all their ſufferings, a good od, a good Cauſe, and a good Conſcience, will carry them chearfully
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:44418:57"/> through all their troubles, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly quiet and ſupport their ſpirits. And the leaſt glimpſe of God's recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled countenance in Chriſt, will infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely compenſate for all the frowns and fury of implacable Adverſaries; inward comforts will make amends for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward troubles. A good Conſcience, like <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> will bring good tidings; or like a Halcyon, (as is ſaid) appears in a ſtorm, as an emblem of a calm ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching. Or a good Conſcience may reſemble <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove, which brought an Olive-leaf in her mouth, in token that the waters were abated. As <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod ſwallowed up all the Rods of the Magicians; ſo a pacified Conſcience, by the conſolations of God's ſpirit, will ſwallow up all manner of troubles and vexations whatſoever. A ſincere heart, and the anſwer of a good conſcience, and the apprehenſion of God's recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled countenance in the face of Chriſt, will compoſe and quiet our ſpirits, and becalm and make them ſedate, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle all manner of fluctuating and tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuating thoughts. To this purpoſe I'le cite an excellent paſſage of St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſis varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laniantur cogitationes meae, intimae viſcera a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimae, meae donet in te coajinam purgatus &amp; li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>uidus g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e amoris tui.</hi> Aug. conf. l. c. 29.</note> My thoughts (ſaith he) are torn in pieces with variety of tumults, even my inward bowels are torn in pieces,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44418:58"/> until I make haſte to be purged, and and melted with the fire of thy love.</q> One only word ſpoken by Chriſt, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly becalm'd a rough and tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sea; for when the Diſciples were afraid, <hi>Matth. 8. 26. Chriſt aroſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked the Winds and the Sea, and there was a great calm.</hi> And amidſt variety of ſtorms and tempeſts, even ſuch winds which blow fiercer than that called <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclydon,</hi> Acts 27. 17. Chriſt can make all ſtill: and ſo can he amidſt the greateſt inward and ſharpeſt ſtorms of Chriſtians (when they are at their wits end, and know not what to do) Chriſt (I ſay) can ſpeak a word of peace unto their Souls, ſaying, <hi>Son, or Daughter, be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, all thy ſins are forgiven thee.</hi> Upon the hearing of ſuch a gracious word, there will follow a marvelous tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſerenity upon the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> It cannot be denied (though it ought to be bewailed) but the beſt of Saints here on earth have their ſpots and fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; for they are encompaſſed in this World with a body of ſin and corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, yet they are ſenſible of, and mourn for their ſpots and failings, (for they are their ſorrow, and their heavy burthen.) They do not willingly allow themſelves in any ſin, nor willingly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44418:58"/> from any command. Sin in a Child of God is a torment to him, like a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken leg, or a broken tooth; it's matter of dolour and anguiſh to him. Sin in a Child of God, is like Garbidge thrown into a running ſtream, it is ſtill running and purging away of all manner of filth and impurity. But ſin in an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man is like Garbidge thrown into a ſtanding pond, there it abides, and ſends forth a loathſome and ſtinking ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. However, all thoſe whoſe hearts are upright with God, make it their continual employment to ſearch their hearts, and to waſh and cleanſe them: hereupon after ſearching of their hearts, they learn to know them better; and they know more evil by themſelves than all the World can tell them of; hence follows heart-compunction, ſighing and mourning. And being thus apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of their own impotency and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs, and forlorn condition, they make haſte to Chriſt, and implore his gracious aſſiſtance; and beſeech him to cleanſe them, and make them white in his Bloud. Wherefore as often as that inveterate enemy Satan, and all mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and ungodly men, the Devils in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, prefer large Bills of Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and falſe Indictments againſt the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:44418:59"/> Saints, they make their appeal to the righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, who alwaies judgeth righteouſly. The Apoſtle makes an expoſtulation, and gives an anſwer thereunto every way ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, <hi>Rom. 8. 33, 34. Who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? it is God that juſtifieth.</hi> The moſt bitter Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations, and moſt violent Perſecutions of them all are altogether inſignificant, and of no effect, force or vertue, againſt any of thoſe whom God juſtifies: for Gods juſtification and diſcharge will fully acquit and exonerate us, and ſave us harmleſs and indemnified againſt all the demands, charges, ſuggeſtions, and libels made againſt us by the worſt of Enemies. For it follows in the next words; <hi>Who is he that condemneth? it is Christ that died, yea rather that is riſen again, who is even at the right hand of God, who alſo maketh interceſſion for us.</hi> The frequent and ſerious meditation of theſe things, abundantly ſupport and comfort the godly in their Pilgrimage on Earth. Albeit the beſt of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren meet with conflicts and antipathies, and are excerciſed in combats againſt the Fleſh, the Devil, and the World, thoſe ſpiritual Enemies of their Salvation, yet through the ſtrength of Chriſt they ſhall
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:44418:59"/> return with Trophies of Victory; and by experience they ſhall find the fleſh to be weaker and weaker, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſtronger: as it was ſaid of the houſes of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Saul,</hi> this grew weaker and weaker, and the other grew ſtronger and ſtronger. But whilſt we are in this World we muſt never caſt down our weapons, but ſtill continue fighting againſt ſin; we muſt not expect to reſt from our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours till we are dead. Let's then with all diligence and fidelity manage our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual warfare, and in all things labour to approve our hearts ſincere to God, and we ſhall at length conclude with the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 8, 37. Nay, in all theſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>things we are more then conquerors, through him that loved us.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:44418:60"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Containing the Comforts which ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere-hearted Perſons enjoy in their Deaths.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> HAving repreſented in the former Chapter the great comforts which ſuch whoſe hearts are ſincere with God receive in their lives, in the ſecond place I come to diſcover the comforts of them in their deaths: Although by no means may we make a judgment of the courſe of the life, by reaſon of ſome diſtempers and paſſions which oftentimes proceed from ſtrength of Diſeaſes; yet uſually we read of the deliberate, compoſed and ſerious profeſſions of many good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which they have made on the bed of languiſhing. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov. 14. 32. The righteous hath hope in his death.</hi> And hope grounded on Divine promiſes affords us ſuperabundant conſolation. When the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was ſent to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> to give him warning of his death, which was ſuddenly approaching, then <hi>Hezekiah</hi> recollects his ſerious thoughts,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44418:60"/> and reflects upon his upright walking with God in his whole life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; the remembrance whereof ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred ground of ſingular conſolation unto his Soul. The Hiſtory is on record in holy Scripture; 2 <hi>Kings 20. 1, 2, 3. In thoſe days was</hi> Hezekiah <hi>ſick unto death: and the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah <hi>the ſon of</hi> Amos <hi>came to him, and ſaid unto him, Set thine houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die and not live. Then he turned his face unto the wall, and prayed unto the Lord, ſaying, I beſeech thee, O Lord, remember now how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and have done that which was good in thy ſight.</hi> Likewiſe St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the time of his diſſolution to draw near, thus raiſeth to himſelf a ground of ſtrong conſolation, 2 <hi>Tim. 4. 7, 8. For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand: I have fought a good fight, I have finiſhed my courſe, I have kept the faith; henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of righteouſneſs, which the Lord the righteous Judge ſhall give me at that day, and not to me only, but unto all them that love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing.</hi> We commonly ſay, That the houſe of Death is the houſe of Truth; and where the ſenſes are exerciſed, and the memory and judgment are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:44418:61"/> there will be plain dealing, and there will be made plain diſcoveries. As for ſuch (for them only I now mention) whoſe hearts are upright with God, the remembrance of the ſincerity of their hearts, next to the conſolations of Gods ſpirit, will revive their ſpirits on their beds of languiſhing.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> Let us conſider before hand, that we ſhall all die; for Death is the common lot and portion of all mankind, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 27. it is Gods appointment: Would we not then be glad when we are caſt upon our Death-beds, to have ſomething at that time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o comfort us? when we are leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe houſes of Clay, and unclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our ſelves of our mortal Bodies, what is that which will be a ground of comfort to bear up our ſpirits? Will thouſands of Gold and Silver purchaſe the Favour of God? can the greateſt Mannors, Lordſhips, and Revenues of the World? Can an Imperial Diadem b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Death to ſtay a longer time? Can all the Grandees and Poten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates of this World, ſhould they all unite as one man, avail any thing to make our peace with God? No, queſtionleſs: For no great Perſonages, nor great Riches, can either d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er themſelves or us from the ſtroke of Death, nor pacifie their own
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:44418:61"/> nor our Conſciences, nor make any peace and reconciliation either for themſelves or for us at that day. Some in this World being arreſted for Debt, have made the Serjeant drunk, and ſo have made an eſcape out of his hands. But it is altogether impoſſible to deal ſo with the grim Serjeant Death; none can eſcape Deaths dart, wherever they run Death will ſtrike them to the heart. Now then, when all the Gold and Silver which the Univerſe can afford, when all the intereſt of Friends, though great and potent, cannot adminiſter any comfort, peace and ſatisfaction to us when we lie upon our Death-beds, then Oh then! is that neceſſary inſtant, when the light of Gods gracious countenance, ſhining upon us in the face of Chriſt, can only revive our ſpirits, and give us real and durable joy, peace and comfort; when all creature comforts are Phyſicians of <note place="margin">Job 13. 4.</note> no value, empty Cyphers, inſufficient and unable to give us any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This then is that good which the Pſalmiſt had experienced, and prayed for it above all beſides, <hi>Pſal. 4. 6, 7, 8. There be many that ſay, Who will ſhew us any good? Lord, lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon us. Thou hast put gladneſs in my heart, more then in the</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:44418:62"/> 
                  <hi>time that their corn and wine increaſed. I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſpice nos ſereao vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, oſtende te nobis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, recipe no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lare to, lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifica no. tuâ praeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ: id non famus ſoliciti quid fiat in hoc mundo, car impit per veni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at ad ſummas ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp; ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerus.</note> 
                  <hi>will both lay me down in peace and ſleep; for thou Lord only makest me dwell in ſafety.</hi> Hence it evidently appears, that the only ſaving good conſiſts in the light of Gods gracious countenance. For this we muſt be earneſt and indefatigable ſolicitors at the Throne of Grace: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the men of the World may frown on us, and the Riches of the World may forſake us, yet if God ſmile on us, and be reconciled to us in Chriſt, he will never leave us nor forſake us, no not when we are gray-headed, and upon our beds of languiſhing; and when our natural ſtrength fails, and our diſeaſes do much afflict us, and the pains thereof make us roar, the reflection of our well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent time in giving up our ſtrength to the ſervice of God, and of improving of our health to glorifie God, will be even our Death-beds ſingular ground of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, even the reviving of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of ſuch time, ſtrength, and health ſo imployed in the ſervice of God. When the faithfuleſt of our Friends, and ſuch as are moſt willing to do us good, are not able to help us at all; when learned Phyſicians have given us over, as alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether deſperate and incurable; and when the pains and pangs of a long,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44418:62"/> waſting, lingring and tormenting diſeaſe, even a complication of diſeaſes are inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible, and our throats rattle, and the abundance of Phlegm is ready to ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate us, and our eye-ſtrings are ready to break, and our eyes are dim and gaſtly, and every breath we take (though with much difficulty) is like to be our laſt breathing. Oh! then is the time that <hi>the teſtimony of a good conſcience,</hi> that (as the Apoſtle profeſſeth, 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 12.) in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, and in godly ſincerity, we had our converſation in this world,</hi> will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly comfort us; and the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the love of God in Chriſt will revive our fainting ſpirits, and give ſtrength in our weakneſs, and raiſe up our ſpirits, and make us couragious, that we ſhall not be afraid of Death, <hi>the King of terrors;</hi> which though it be terrible in it ſelf, and (as the Philoſopher ſaith) <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the moſt terrible of all terrible things;</hi> yet through the mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, Death is a conquer'd Enemy; Chriſt hath conquer'd Death, and took away its ſting. That which makes Death ſo terrible, is the ſting of ſin; but when the ſting is took away, Death can no more hurt us than a Snake that hath loſt its ſting, or an Adder that hath its teeth knockt out. The Apoſtle cries out,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44418:63"/> 1 <hi>Cor. 15. 55, 56, 57. O Death, where is thy ſting? O Grave, where is thy victory? The ſting of Death is ſin, and the ſtrength of ſin is the Law. But thanks be to God, which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> What is Death to a Child of God, reconciled to him by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hriſt? <q rend="margQuotes">It's no more (as a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing Saint expreſt) then a Child of God can embrace with both his arms:</q> And he cloſing his arms together died immediately. To a Child of God Death is the greateſt preferment; by Death he is tranſlated from a vale of tears and miſery, to everlaſting happineſs. It's like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gaol-delivery, which delivers the Soul from the Bodies impriſonment, and ſets it at liberty to enjoy the happineſs amongſt Saints in glory. VVhat's then the grand duty incumbent on us all? It is thus: If we would deſire to die happily, we muſt live holily; if we would die the death of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ghteous, we muſt labour to live the life of the righteous: we ſhould ſo live every day, as we deſire to be ſound at the laſt day. And if we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire comfort in our death, we muſt make daily preparation, by approving our hearts to God in a holy and circumſpect life and converſation. It is a very great mercy and condeſcenſion in God, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44418:63"/> Evangelical inſtead of Legal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and to accept of a willing mind inſtead of real performances. For we read, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 17. that <hi>by faith</hi> Abraham, <hi>when he was tried, offered up</hi> Iſaac. And likewiſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If there be a willing mind it is accepted, according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi> When then we come to die, to conſider that our hearts are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere with God, and that our peace is made with him by the redemption and interceſſion of Chriſt, and that all our ſins are waſht away, and we are made white in the Bloud of the Lamb, theſe Meditations will comfort us in Life and in Death.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> Let's add hereunto for incouragement and comfort to the living, the dying Speeches of many eminent Saints, who upon their Death-beds breath'd forth ſnch ſavoury Speeches, which ought to be had in everlaſting remembrance. I ſhall gather ſparingly from ſo great a heap, and only ſelect ſome choice In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which deſerve a ſpecial remark to be ſet upon them.</p>
               <p>Old <hi>Simeon's</hi> Song was ſweet before his Funeral, ſaying, <hi>Luke 2. 29, 30. Lord, now lettest thou thy Servant depart in peace, according to thy Word; for mine eyes have ſeen thy Salvation,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:44418:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen,</hi> the Protomartyr, breath'd forth this dying Prayer, <hi>Acts 7. 59. Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who liv'd in the ſirſt Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Vid. Ignat. epiſt. ad Rom.</note> who was (as the Eccleſiaſtical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſay) twelve years of age when Chriſt was crucified, and afterward St. <hi>John</hi>'s Auditor, uſed frequently to ſay, <hi>My Love is crucified.</hi> And when he was brought to Martyrdom, and the wild Beaſts were let looſe to tear him in pieces, he coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">I am the Wheat or Grain to be ground with the teeth of Beaſts, that I may be pure Bread for my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters tooth: Let fire, rack, pullies, yea and all the torments of Hell come on me, ſo I may win Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Polycarpus,</hi> when the Proconſul urged him to deny Chriſt, anſwered, <q rend="margQuotes">I have ſerved Chriſt Eighty ſix years, and he hath not done me hurt, and ſhall I now deny him?</q> When they would have tied him to the Stake to be burned, he deſired to ſtand untied, ſaying, <q rend="margQuotes">Let me alone, I pray you; for he that gave me ſtrength to come to this fire, will alſo give me patience to abide in the ſame, without your tying.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian,</hi> that eminent Martyr for the truth, after his condemnation, ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">Bleſſed be God for this Gaol-delivery.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:44418:64"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> on his Death bed, ſaid to his Friends about him, <q rend="margQuotes">I have not ſo lived, that I am aſhamed to live any longer; nor fear I death, becauſe I have a good Lord.</q> Some young men ſeeing the excellent death of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and hearing what rare ſpeeches he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, one of thoſe young men turned to his fellow, and ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">Oh! that I might live with you, and die with him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Lambert,</hi> a Martyr in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>'s daies, ſaid amidſt the flame, <q rend="margQuotes">None but Chriſt, none but Chriſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bradford,</hi> at the Stake in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> embraced the Reeds and Fagots which were ſuddenly to be ſet on fire to burn him, and ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">Strait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way that leadeth unto Life, and few there be that find it.</q> And he encouraged his fellow-Martyr, ſaying, <q rend="margQuotes">Be of good comfort, Brother, for we ſhall have a merry Supper with the Lord this night: If there be any way to Heaven on horſe-back, or in fiery Chariots, this is it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> that great ſcourge of the Pope, and Champion ſor the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, on his Death-bed ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">Thee, O Chriſt, have I taught, thee have I truſted, thee have I loved; into thy hands I commend my ſpirit.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:44418:65"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bucer,</hi> an eminent Reformer, ſaid ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> his death, <q rend="margQuotes">No man by talk ſhall with draw my mind from Chriſt crucified from Heaven, and my ſpeedy Depa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, on which my Soul is fixed.</q> Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one adviſed him to arm himſelf again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans temptations, he anſwered, <q rend="margQuotes">Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan hath nothing to do with me; Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> forbid but that now my Soul ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be ſure of ſweet conſolation.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Ardley,</hi> a Martyr in Queen <hi>Mary'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ſaid, <q rend="margQuotes">If every hair of my hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> were a man, it ſhould ſuffer death i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the faith I now ſtand in.</q> To the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> purpoſe <hi>William Sparrow</hi> ſpake, and <hi>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Stanley.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alice Driver,</hi> when the Chain was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her Neck, <q rend="margQuotes">Here is (ſaith ſhe) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> goodly Neckerchief, bleſſed be Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Noyes,</hi> a Martyr, kiſſing the Stake ſain, <q rend="margQuotes">Bleſſed be God that ever I wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> born for this day.</q> And he added far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his fellow Martyrs a word of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular conſolation, ſaying, <q rend="margQuotes">We ſhal not loſe our lives in this fire, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> change them for a better; and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Coals have P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arls. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>What need I produce any more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances? with what joy have many ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere hearted Chriſtians lookt death in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44418:65"/> the face, ſo that they had rather die than live?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Melancthon</hi> rejoyced when he was to die, ſaying; <hi>That he ſhould be with Chriſt, and enjoy fellowſhip with him and the Church triumphant; and then be freed from all thoſe hot diſputes and contentions of Divines, which were very great in thoſe days.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Grynaeus,</hi> a great Scholar, when he came to die, ſaid; <hi>O happy day, when I may depart out of this troubleſome and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful world, and to go to thoſe bleſſed Souls before departed.</hi> He writing to his friend <hi>Chytraeus,</hi> ſaid; <hi>If we never ſee one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again in this world, yet we ſhall meet in that place where</hi> Luther <hi>and</hi> Zuinglius <hi>agree very well together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bolton</hi> on his dying b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſaid; <hi>I am now drawing on apace to my diſſolution: Hold out faith and patience, your work will quickly be attained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That great Magazine of Learning Mr. <hi>John Selden,</hi> when he came to die, ſaid; <hi>That he accounted all his Learning nothing at all in compariſon of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Giles Workman,</hi> a worthy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Gloceſter ſhire,</hi> a little before his death ſaid; <hi>That he had a little ſincerity of heart, and that was a comfort to him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:44418:66"/>
               <p>Mr. <hi>John Ferriby,</hi> a Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> when he was dying ſaid; <hi>That he left his Wife and Children with God, and his gracious promiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Gifford,</hi> a Miniſter in <hi>Northam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton-ſhire,</hi> ſaid to his Children upon his Death-bed; <hi>That if they feared God,</hi> (to which he earneſtly exhorted them) <hi>they ſhould not want; but if they did not fear God, he wiſht that they might want till they did fear him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Samuel Hieron,</hi> a rare Miniſter, (whoſe excellent writings praiſe him in the gate) on his Death-bed ſaid; <hi>That the ſame God who took care for the Ravens and Sparrows, would likewiſe take care for the young</hi> Hierons.</p>
               <p>And ſo it came to paſs, for God ſtirred up the hearts of ſome charitably affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted perſons, who carefully educated his Children; and ſo thoſe young <hi>Hierons</hi> were well provided for.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this head with the words of the Pſalmiſt; <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints,</hi> Pſal. 116. 15. <hi>Surely he ſhall not be moved for ever; the righteous ſhall be in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remembrance,</hi> Pſal. 112. 6. And I will only add words of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 10. 9. <hi>The memory of the just is bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:44418:66"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Containing the Happineſs of the Saints in Heaven; or the inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible Conſolations which the Godly, even all ſincere-hearted Perſons, enjoy in Heaven to all Eternity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the third and laſt place, let's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, <note place="margin">3. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of the godly afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> death. Sect. 1.</note> or rather admire at the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, even the perfection of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and happineſs, which the Saints ſhall enjoy after death in the higheſt Heavens to all eternity. As for all thoſe who lived in hypocriſie and diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and lived without repentance, and ſo died; and as for all ſuch who lived without God in the world, having no fear of God before their eyes, but have committed ſin with greedineſs, and have run into all exceſs of riot, and ſo die in their unbelief and impenitency, theſe are the Goats which ſhall ſtand on Chriſts left hand; and againſt them he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that dreadful ſentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, <hi>Matth 25. 41. Depart from</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:44418:67"/> 
                  <hi>me, ye curſed, into everlaſting fire, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> But all upright and ſincere-hearted Chriſtians, who are only Chriſts ſheep, they ſhall ſtand at Chriſts right hand; and he will pronounce to them that comfortable ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raviſhing ſentence of abſolution; <hi>Come, ye bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world,</hi> verſe 34.</p>
               <p>However ſuch who are Gods Jewels, and precious in ſight, are viliſied and trampled on by the wicked of the world, as if they were no better than <hi>the filth of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 13. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>the world, and the off-ſcouring of all things<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> yet at the general reſurrection, both of juſt and unjuſt, there will be a reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the names and of the cauſes of the righteous, however in this world they have been traduced and ſcorned. Then the meaneſt of glorified Saints (whom this world thought they could not think bad enough) ſhall have the preheminence and ſuperiority above all the ungodly, though they have been never ſo great in this preſent world; for (ſo ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 49. 14.) the upright ſhall have dominion over them in the morning.</hi> From this Scripture it plainly appears, that at the general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection the godly ſhall be known to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:44418:67"/> the whole world to have dominion and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quamvis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>c demer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis ſit i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ebris mund is, ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tur ſubito n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> manè quod faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em verae &amp; ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>etaae v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>obis reſtituet.</hi> Calv. in Loc.</note> preheminence above all the ungod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y men of this world. And that all ſuch who truly fear God, though in this world they were in a poor and abject condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet at that great day they ſhall be in a better condition, every way rich and honourable, and infinitely happier than any ungodly, great, and rich men can be in this preſent world.</p>
               <p>Farther, the godly in glory ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of nothing elſe but joy and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the perfection of both; but damned wretches ſhall be for ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar'd from all manner of joy, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of nothing elſe but hopeleſs ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and endleſs miſery. At the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Judgment, when all without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception <hi>ſhall appear before the Judgment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>of Christ,</hi> then there ſhall appear a great and wide difference between g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od and bad, chaff and wheat, ſheep and goats: that day will make a great and clear diſtinction. Then all the Enemies of Chriſt and of his Church, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced in perſecuting Chriſt here on Earth in his Members, would be glad to creep into holes (if poſſible) that they might hide themſelves from the wrath of the Lamb. Then they will wiſh that the mountains might fall upon them,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44418:68"/> and that Rocks and Hills, Dens or Caves might ſhelter and cover them from the face of the Lamb incenſed againſt them. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe bloudy Perſecutors of Chriſt <hi>ſhall ſee him whom they have pierced,</hi> zech. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. <hi>Judas,</hi> who betrayed Chriſt with a hypocritical kiſs; <hi>Pilate,</hi> who (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the reluctancy of his own conſcience) condemned Chriſt to pleaſe the people, and releaſed <hi>Barabb as,</hi> an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Thief and Murtherer; the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who crucified him; and after they had firſt been his Executioners, were his Executors to take his Garments: All theſe, and all other Enemies of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall ſee him at that <hi>great Day</hi> to their terror and condemnation. Thoſe giddy-pated people, who a little before cried to Chriſt <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> and afterwards cried, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him,</hi> ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before Chriſts Judgment-ſeat, and then receive their ſentence. Thoſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Jews, who wiſht that <hi>the bloud of Chriſt might be upon them, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> (except ſuch only who are waſht in Chriſt's bloud) ſhall to their dread, and horror be condemn'd for embrewing their hands in the innocent bloud of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> At the day of Judgment all falſ Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and unrighteous ſentences paſt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:44418:68"/> on earth ſhall be reverſt. Pontius Pilate who paſt an unjuſt judgment againſt Chriſt, ſhall have a juſt judgment paſt upon him. <hi>Luther</hi> uſed to ſay, that <hi>At the day of Judgment,</hi> John Huſs <hi>and</hi> Jerome <note place="margin">Luth. Loc. Com.</note> 
                  <hi>of</hi> Prague <hi>ſhall appear to be good men, when the Pope and his Cardinalls ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be vile, and wicked wretches.</hi> St <hi>Bernard</hi> uſ'd to ſay. <hi>That the Day will</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Veniet Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet Dies quando ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le judicata rejudicabit Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> Bern.</note> 
                  <hi>come, it will certainly come, when God will judg over again all falſe judgment.</hi> But as for all thoſe whoſe hearts were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right with God, whilſt they liv'd in this world, theſe after death are tranſlated into an eſtate of glory and happineſs, and in the higheſt heavens receive conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beyond all expreſſion, and <hi>a weight of glory</hi> beyond the capacity of any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal man, which Chriſt gives to all his Children, who in their Pilgrimage on earth, endeavoured with their whole heart, and ſtrength, to ſerve the Lord in ſincerity, and in truth. All thoſe who were on earth Sincere-hearted, and real Saints, ſhall be acknowledged to be ſuch by Chriſt himſelf at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. No ſin, no failing, nor imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall at all be layd to their Charge in that day; for all failings and ſins, and all manner of imperfections ſhall be waſht away in the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt. What
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44418:69"/> ever good things the Saints have done on earth, ſhall be all remembred, and not any one thing forgotten at the day of judgment. But whatever was bad and ſinfull that they committed on earth, ſhall not be layd to their Charge, but ſhall be blotted out of the Book of <hi>Gods Remembrance,</hi> and God will caſt them into the depth of the ſea. O: What a joyfull day, and full of Comfort will the day of judgment be to all the Children of God! Then they ſhall lift up their heads with Comfort and behold him who is their Judg, as their <hi>Redeemer, Advocate, Interceſſor, and Flder Brother,</hi> and he will pronounce for them a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Abſolution. At that day, all glorified Saints ſhall have their bodily eyes irradiated with the ſplendor of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and they ſhall be inabled to behold the Beatificall Viſion, and this is he Happineſs of all Happineſs, and this only is their portion, and appropriated to them alone who are <hi>pure in heart.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y are bleſſed (as our Saviour pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth them) <hi>Who are pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> Then the Saints in glory ſhall ſit in Judgment as Aſſeſſors with Chriſt, and ſhall approve of the righteous ſentence of Chriſt in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning their unrighteous Judges.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44418:69"/> Then they ſhall ſee the Omniporent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Jehovah, the Beeing of all Beeings the firſt perſon in Trinity uncreated, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten, and unproceeding: Then they ſhall ſee Chriſt the Mediator of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> New Covenant, their only Saviour and Redeemer uncreated, but begotten, and not proceeding, who is the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in Trinity: Then they ſhall ſee the holy Ghoſt the third Perſon in Trinity neither created, nor begotten, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from both. The Glorifyd Saints (what they believed when they were militant on earth) ſhall in heaven underſtand the great Myſtery of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity. One glorified Saint ſhall know more, then all the Learned men in the world. I'le conclude with this Doxology.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now to the holy and bleſſed Trinity, and one God in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all Honour and Glory, Praiſe and Thanksgiving, Dominion and Obedience, henceforth and unto all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Amen,</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:70"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:70"/>
            <head>THE Contents of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF ſpiritual poverty</hi> p. 1.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>Spiritual poverty conſiſts in empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the heart of what is ſelf</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect II. <hi>Every humble ſpirited man is low, vile and abject in his own eyes</hi> p. 3.</item>
               <item>Sect. III. <hi>One who is ſpiritually poor, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates frequently and ſeriouſly upon the promiſes, and makes particular applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them</hi> p. 6.</item>
               <item>Sect. IV. <hi>One that is poor in ſpirit is weak, fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k, and in a diſtreſſed condition as to his own apprehenſion, and makes haſte unto Christ for help</hi> p. 9.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Concerning the higheſt prizing and valuing</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44418:71"/> 
                  <hi>of Jeſus Christ</hi> p. 11.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>It's an infallible ſign of a true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever to value and prefer Christ before all the riches of the world</hi> p. 11.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Of ard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ney and ſtrength of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Jeſus Christ</hi> p. 14.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of a heart in love with holineſs, evidenced in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> holy life and converſation</hi> p. 16.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>Every true Believer loves holineſs for it ſelf, becauſe it is the image of God</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Where holineſs is in the heart, it is fruitful in the life</hi> p. 19.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of ingenuous ſorrow for ſin</hi> p. 24.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>Ingenuous ſorrow is more for the ſin than the puniſhment</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>There is a great difference between the mournings of</hi> Cain, Ahab. Judas, <hi>&amp;c. and the mournings of.</hi> David, Paul, Peter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 25.</item>
               <item>Sect. III. <hi>There's a great difference between the mourning of ſlaves and mourning of children</hi> p. 30.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:71"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of ſorrowing and mourning for others ſins</hi> p. 33.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>A godly mourner mourns for others ſins</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>We must be affected with, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted for the ſins of others, remembring that we are men of like paſſions</hi> p. 37.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of approving our hearts unto God</hi> p. 42.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>A ſincere-he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rted Chriſtian labours to aprove his heart to God, and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon God's trial</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Though we are ſubject to many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, we must groan under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of them</hi> p. 44.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of preſſing forward towards perfection</hi> p. 49.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>It's an Apoſtolical character, and Apoſtolical practice, to preſs forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards perfection</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Inſtances in particulars whether we preſs forward towards perfection</hi> p. 52.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of a ſtrict watch ſet upon the heart against boſome ſins</hi> p. 55.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>A ſincere heart endeavors to keep it ſelf from every beloved ſin</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>No ſin ſo little but deſerves dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>Sect. III. <hi>An illuſtration by ſimilitudes</hi> p. 61.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>An endeavor against every ſin, and for the practice of every duty</hi> p. 65.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>The deſire and endeavor must be against every ſin</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>The endeavor must be to obey all commands, and practice all duties</hi> p. 69.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of a heart without guile</hi> p. 73.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>The heart must be without guile</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Every perſon that is upright is compounded of three words,</hi> viz. <hi>ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, ſingleneſs, and ſincerity</hi> p. 74.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:44418:72"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of mortification of the deeds of the body</hi> p. 80.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>The deeds of the body,</hi> i. e. <hi>all luſts ought to be mortified</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Queſtions propounded and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> p. 83.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Viviſication of the fruits of the Spirit</hi> p. 91.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>Beſide mortification of the deeds of the body, there muſt be a vivification of the fruits of the Spirit</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>How this is to be diſcerned</hi> p. 93.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Containing the comforts of ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> p. 95.</item>
               <item>Sect I. <hi>Sincere Chriſtians have comforts in their lives</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>Sincere Chriſtians are ſenſible of their ſins, and mourn for them</hi> p. 98.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XIV.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sincere-hearted Chriſtians have comforts in their deaths</hi> p. 102.</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>The comfortable deaths of ſuch as</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:44418:73"/> 
                  <hi>are ſincere</hi> p. 102</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>We ought to prepare for deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> p. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Sect. III. <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ying ſpeeches of Saints</hi> p. 109</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Containing the happineſs of the Saints i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Heaven</hi> p. 115</item>
               <item>Sect. I. <hi>The Saints in Heaven receive per fection of happineſs</hi> ibid</item>
               <item>Sect. II. <hi>At the day of Judgment all fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> judgments ſhall be reverſt</hi> p. 118</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44418:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
